<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>kareem&#39;s Blog</title>
<link>https://kareemai.com/blog/feed.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://kareemai.com/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Kareem Elkhateb personal site, a blog about machine learning, deep learning, Web developement with Astrojs,fastapi aslo arabic Natural Language Processing and Rust language.</description>
<image>
<url>https://kareemai.com/quarto.png</url>
<title>kareem&#39;s Blog</title>
<link>https://kareemai.com/blog/feed.html</link>
<height>86</height>
<width>144</width>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.6.40</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 22:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>فن تبسيط الحياة الرقمية</title>
  <dc:creator>kareem </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/digital_minimalisim_arabic.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<ul>
<li><h1 id="لماذا-نمد-أيدينا-بشكل-غريزي-إلى-هواتفنا-خلال-لحظات-الملل-أو-الفراغ">لماذا نمد أيدينا بشكل غريزي إلى هواتفنا خلال لحظات الملل أو الفراغ؟</h1>
<p>ليس من قبيل الصدفة. تم تصميم التطبيقات لجذبنا مرة أخرى، والحفاظ على انتباهنا وتقديم دفعات من الدوبامين أثناء استخدامها.</p>
<p>ومع ذلك، فإن مجرد معرفة ذلك لا يمنعنا من تشتيت انتباهنا.</p>
<p>في هذه المقالة، سأشارك العديد من التطبيقات المفيدة والنصائح العملية للتخلص من هذه المشكلة أو تقليل خطرها بقدر الإمكان:</p></li>
<li><h2 id="أوقف-تشغيل-الإشعارات" class="anchored">1. أوقف تشغيل الإشعارات</h2>
<ul>
<li>الإشعارات هي بوابة المشتتات.</li>
<li>معظم الإشعارات غير مهمة ولكنها تخلق شعورًا زائفًا بالإلحاح.</li>
<li>بدلاً من مراجعة إشعارات كل تطبيق على حدة، من الأسهل تبني عقلية أن جميع الإشعارات يجب أن تكون متوقفة بشكل افتراضي.</li>
<li>أوقف تشغيل كل شيء أولاً، ثم قم بتمكين الإشعارات فقط للتطبيقات الأساسية مثل المراسلة والتقويم.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><h2 id="استخدم-أيقونات-سوداء-ومصغرة" class="anchored">2. استخدم أيقونات سوداء ومصغرة</h2>
<ul>
<li>تأتي كافة الواجهات بأيقونات كبيرة وملونة، يمكنك معرفة التطبيق بمجرد اللون فقط، فاللون الأصفر هو تطبيق سناب شات واللون البنفسجي هو الإنستجرام.</li>
<li>يمكنك فتح متجر الثيمات الخاص بجهازك الشخصي وتغيير الأيقونات للون ثابت وموحد، يفضل أسود أو رمادي.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><h2 id="أزل-التطبيقات-من-الشاشة-الرئيسية" class="anchored">3. أزل التطبيقات من الشاشة الرئيسية</h2>
<ul>
<li>على غرار بيئتنا المادية، فإن ما هو موجود على شاشتنا الرئيسية يصبح إشارات تحفز عاداتنا.</li>
<li>عندما تكون تطبيقات الوسائط الاجتماعية مرئية بشكل كبير على شاشتك الرئيسية، فمن المرجح أن تفتحها.</li>
<li>نوصي بنقل التطبيقات المشتتة للانتباه إلى “الخلف”.</li>
<li>يمكن لمستخدمي أيفون إزالة التطبيقات من الشاشة الرئيسية وتخزينها في مكتبة التطبيقات، بينما يمكن لمستخدمي أندرويد الاحتفاظ بالتطبيقات بالمثل في درج التطبيقات.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><h2 id="شغل-فلتر-التدرج-الرمادي" class="anchored">4. شغّل فلتر التدرج الرمادي</h2>
<ul>
<li>يمكن أن يؤدي تحويل هاتفك إلى التدرج الرمادي إلى جعل التمرير عبر الوسائط الاجتماعية أقل تشتيتًا على الفور.</li>
<li>لكنك لست مضطرًا لإبقائه قيد التشغيل طوال الوقت.</li>
<li>نحن نعلم مدى قوة هذه الأجهزة الصغيرة للعمل الإبداعي والترفيه.</li>
<li>ما نوصي به هو وجود طريقة بسيطة لتشغيل وإيقاف فلتر التدرج الرمادي، مثل إضافته إلى مركز التحكم على أجهزة iPhone.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><h2 id="خد-نفسك---أخر-فتح-التطبيقات" class="anchored">5. خد نفسك - أخّر فتح التطبيقات</h2>
<ul>
<li>لإضافة تأخير عند فتح التطبيقات، يمكنك استخدام تطبيق مثل: <a href="https://one-sec.app/">One Sec</a></li>
<li>يقدم التطبيق وقفة قصيرة في كل مرة تحاول فيها فتح الوسائط الاجتماعية أو التطبيقات الأخرى المحددة.</li>
<li>يعمل كحاجز شاشة مؤقت بينك وبين المشتتات، مما يساعدك على إمساك نفسك وتحديد ما إذا كنت مشتتًا أو متعمدًا.</li>
<li>يمكنك استخدام التطبيق على الموبايل أو على الحاسوب.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/images/image_1738724671871_0.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>One Sec</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ul>
<li><h2 id="احذف-التطبيقات-غير-الضرورية" class="anchored">6. احذف التطبيقات غير الضرورية</h2>
<ul>
<li>إذا كان التطبيق المشتت للانتباه لا يضيف أي قيمة حقيقية، فإن الحل الأبسط غالبًا ما يكون الأفضل.</li>
<li>احذفه من جهازك تمامًا.</li>
<li>ثم، استخدم وقتك الذي تم تحريره حديثًا في أنشطة مفيدة.</li>
<li>من التجارب المثيرة هي حذف تطبيق اليوتيوب من الموبايل واستخدامه من المتصفح، سيقلل هذا من الانغماس ويفضل حذف كلا من المتصفح واليوتيوب!!</li>
<li>يمكنك التخلص من تطبيق اليوتيوب بالكامل على نظام أندرويد بدون عمل روت باستخدام Adb manager.</li>
<li>وعندما تريد مشاهدة اليوتيوب أو باقي وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي، يمكنك استخدام الحاسوب فهو أقل عرضة للتشتت والاستخدام في أوقات مثل قبل النوم أو في أثناء المرحاض أو تناول الطعام في المطبخ مثلاً!</li>
</ul></li>
<li><h2 id="أعد-تشكيل-عالمك-كما-تريد" class="anchored">7. أعد تشكيل عالمك كما تريد</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>إذا ما زلت تريد استخدام بعض التطبيقات، يمكنك التحكم في كيفية العرض وماذا تريد أن ترى وما لا تريد، والتوقف عن التشتت مثلاً.</p></li>
<li><p>بعض إضافات المتصفح التي تسمح لك بتعديل الموقع:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://chromewebstore.google.com/detail/minimal-theme-for-twitter/pobhoodpcipjmedfenaigbeloiidbflp">Minimal theme for twitter</a>: تسمح لك بتغيير إعداد عرض تويتر الخاص بك.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/images/image_1738724457971_0.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Minimal Theme for Twitter</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://chromewebstore.google.com/detail/unhook-remove-youtube-rec/khncfooichmfjbepaaaebmommgaepoid">Unhook</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/images/image_1738724551148_0.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Enhancer for Youtube - 1</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://chromewebstore.google.com/detail/enhancer-for-youtube/ponfpcnoihfmfllpaingbgckeeldkhle?hl=en-US">Enhancer for youtube</a></li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/images/image_1738724511256_0.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Enhancer for Youtube - 2</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ul>
<li><h2 id="مراقبة-الوقت" class="anchored">8. مراقبة الوقت</h2>
<ul>
<li>من التطبيقات المفيدة لمراقبة الوقت على الحاسوب والمفتوحة المصدر أيضًا هي: <a href="https://activitywatch.net/">ActivitWatch</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://activitywatch.net/img/screenshots/screenshot-v0.9.3-activity.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Activity Watch Example</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ul>
<li><h2 id="هاتف-غبي" class="anchored">هاتف غبي</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>يمكنك استخدام تطبيق</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://dumbphone.so/">dumb phone</a></li>
</ul></li>
<li><p>يساعدك التطبيق علي اختيار التطبيقات التي تريد فتحها فقط ويقوم بتغيير الايقونة لتصبح اسم مجرد مما يجعلك اكثر وعيا عند محاولتك فتح التطبيق</p></li>
<li><p>يمكنك تجربة&nbsp;تطبيق الهاتف الغبي&nbsp;باستخدام رابط التنزيل أدناه.</p></li>
<li><div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/images/image_1738731874874_0.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>dumb phone</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></li>
<li><div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/images/image_1738731869245_0.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>dumb phone example</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></li>
<li><div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/images/image_1738731860670_0.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>review of dumb phone</figcaption>
</figure>
</div></li>
<li></li>
</ul></li>
<li><h2 id="مراجع" class="anchored">مراجع</h2>
<ul>
<li>مسلكيات</li>
<li>عمل عميق</li>
<li>تبسيط الحياة الرقمية</li>
<li>فن تبسيط الحياة</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>blogging</category>
  <category>idea_Forge</category>
  <category>publish</category>
  <category>rough_thoughts</category>
  <category>life_style</category>
  <guid>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/digital_minimalisim_arabic.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/images/fake_graviety.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Math Skills For AI</title>
  <dc:creator>kareem </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/math/math_skills_for_AI.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="what-i-aim-to-achieve" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-i-aim-to-achieve">What I Aim to Achieve</h2>
<p>As a graduate with a Computer Science degree, my time has been primarily dedicated to three core areas:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Programming:</strong>&nbsp;I’ve worked extensively with Python, C++, JavaScript, and Rust.</li>
<li><strong>Mathematics:</strong>&nbsp;My studies have encompassed linear algebra, probability, calculus, and discrete mathematics.</li>
<li><strong>Core Computer Science:</strong>&nbsp;I’ve explored topics like databases, networking, and data structures &amp; algorithms.</li>
</ol>
<p>During my final year, I realized there were significant gaps in my understanding, despite the courses and books I’d engaged with. I often wish I could start over, but real life doesn’t have a “retry” button.</p>
<p>Currently, I’m involved in:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>AI Research:</strong>&nbsp;My focus is on medical image preprocessing and natural language processing. I’m also keenly interested in areas like:</p>
<ul>
<li>Federated Learning</li>
<li>Adversarial Neural Networks</li>
<li>Explainable AI (XAI)</li>
<li>Generative Art (specifically Stable Diffusion models, Flux, and ControlNet)</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>Web Development:</strong>&nbsp;I primarily use FastHTML and Astrojs for side projects. I enjoy building things and getting paid for them, as I don’t currently have a formal AI job.</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="the-centrality-of-math-in-ai-research" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-centrality-of-math-in-ai-research">The Centrality of Math in AI Research</h2>
<p>It’s true that in both engineering and research, you can be an excellent software engineer and earn a substantial income without deep mathematical knowledge, possibly more than many mathematicians. However, to be a&nbsp;good&nbsp;researcher, a strong mathematical foundation is crucial. By that, I don’t just mean a superficial understanding of numerous topics. You need a solid grasp of linear algebra and probability, both theoretically and practically. And by “practical,” I mean the ability to translate mathematical concepts into code.</p>
<p>Of course, other topics are relevant, depending on your specific field. For example:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Generative AI:</strong>&nbsp;You’ll often encounter differential equations and advanced probability and statistical models.</li>
</ul>
<p>After reading research papers, you begin to see recurring concepts like conditional probability, Bayes’ theorem, and matrix factorization. But you’ll also find complex, novel, or sometimes even older, techniques that are hard to grasp initially.</p>
<hr>
<p>In my limited time exploring research, I’ve observed that many papers lack significant contributions. Some seem to be primarily workarounds, comparisons of existing models, new data applied to established models, or minor observations. This isn’t inherently bad, but it’s not the kind of impact I’m aiming for. The researchers who are making substantial contributions are often very skilled in&nbsp;both&nbsp;math and coding. They create open-source projects, share their ideas, and actively contribute, like the authors of the Colbert papers in information retrieval. And these contributions are often enabled by math, such as PCA, LORA, and other optimization techniques.</p>
<p>While a strong coding background can certainly be beneficial for optimization and research, I strive for a deeper understanding and to reach a higher level of impact. After all, we only have one life.</p>
<p>I don’t consider myself a “bookworm,” but I genuinely love reading and can become engrossed in books on diverse subjects and levels. I recall reading around four books on linear algebra, completing all the exercises, and summarizing the content. In deep learning, I’ve tackled more than 30 books. For areas like networking, databases, and data structures, I’ve read at least three books on each. When new topics like federated learning, XAI, and adversarial networks emerge, I always read at least one book on each.</p>
<p>If you were to examine my profile, CV, GitHub, or even this blog, you’d probably find that I’m below average for a recent graduate! What’s the problem?</p>
<p>I believe the core issue is that while I’ve read extensively and sometimes coded along with the material, I haven’t committed to projects that demand more time and mental effort. I haven’t really allowed the knowledge to “grow.” For instance, I learned linear algebra theory and did the pen-and-paper exercises, but I didn’t experiment with coding it. And, I didn’t apply the concepts I studied to the fields that truly interested me. There’s also a gap between the libraries we use in deep learning and the underlying skills – they don’t always feel directly connected.</p>
<p>It’s unrealistic to understand every library at a micro-level. But it’s crucial to try and bridge the gap between your fundamental skills and the high-level APIs you use. For example, challenge yourself to implement PCA from scratch with NumPy on a Kaggle dataset. Try coding the matrix components of LORA with PyTorch. Take probability concepts and apply them to datasets you care about – for me, that might be datasets related to fitness or Arabic language processing. Build projects you love using these new tools, and consciously choose what skills to prioritize. For example, I might be okay with letting go of some discrete math knowledge, but not linear algebra.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-days-of-problem-solving" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-days-of-problem-solving">The Days of Problem Solving</h2>
<p>During my second year, I began exploring problem-solving but initially struggled with platforms like Codeforces. However, after two months of encouragement from friends, I decided to give it another shot.</p>
<p>I was using Edabit to practice Python problem-solving with easy problems and then moved to Codeforces without a solid grasp of C++. It took time and many hours struggling with error messages (I once learned a painful lesson that “” and ’’ are different in C++ unlike Python!).</p>
<p>After about two months of this, my skills in both thinking and implementation improved dramatically. I recall one of my earliest achievements was writing a 300-line C++ solution without relying on Google, and of course, LLMs weren’t around at that time. This feeling of self-sufficiency was incredibly rewarding. After four months, my problem-solving skills had improved considerably, and I had reached the next level. However, I then decided to shift my focus to web development to improve my financial situation, and I never went back. I also remember failing a technical interview in my third year because I struggled to solve linked list problems in Python, despite being able to do so in C++. I felt lost throughout my college years</p>
<p>But that feeling of deep understanding, of being able to solve problems independently, is amazing and builds confidence. It’s a virtuous cycle.</p>
</section>
<section id="things-i-remember" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="things-i-remember">Things I Remember</h2>
<p>I’m revisiting linear algebra and realized I’d forgotten how to calculate eigenvalues, though I understand their role. However, I haven’t forgotten how to calculate the determinant of a 2x2 or 3x3 matrix. Why? Because I solved countless exercises with determinants, but with eigenvalues, I had primarily read the solutions or tried simple examples. When using PCA in code, it’s easy to rely on a library and not think about the underlying operations. While that’s okay to some degree, we should occasionally revisit how things work behind the scenes.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-mbzuai-exam-in-two-days" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-mbzuai-exam-in-two-days">The MBZUAI Exam in Two Days</h2>
<p>A friend told me about a scholarship at MBZUAI with a deadline in three days. Although I didn’t have the necessary English test scores, I applied anyway. They’ve scheduled an exam in 7 days from when I applied, and today was the first day I started preparing.</p>
<p>I completed the linear algebra and probability specializations on Coursera taught by Luis G. Serrano. While it was a good refresher, I dislike relearning the same concepts every year! The exam will cover probability, linear algebra, calculus, algorithms, trigonometry, optimization, and some NLP questions.</p>
<p>I honestly don’t remember much about trigonometry, and when I studied it before, it was in Arabic, not English, and the transition isn’t so simple. I also dislike cramming things for two days only to forget them immediately after – that feels like a waste of time.</p>
<p>Despite the odds, I’m determined to apply, even if the acceptance rate for the scholarship is only 5%. Working with the people at MBZUAI would be a great experience. If I’m not accepted, I’ll continue to focus on mastering math and keep moving forward.</p>
</section>
<section id="maslakiat" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="maslakiat">Maslakiat</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/math/images/Maslakiat.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>كتاب مسليكات إبراهيم السكران</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>when i have a stress and a lof of taskes i go to reading books I have final exams in the comming days, MBZUAI exam, research paper review comments needed to be corrected, open source problem i must finish this week, some websites and a lot of things. I start reading the first the page and the author was talking to me and the words touch my soul deeply for example some qoutes from the <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/22363984">book</a> I will write them in arabic and you can translate them with GPT.</p>
<p><strong>Translations of the Arabic Quotes (with slight interpretations for clarity):</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>“ولكن ثمة عامل له في نفسي حفاوة خاصة ، عامل يفسر كثيرا من فشل الطموحات و الأحلام … هذا العامل بكل اختصار: هو أن الخطط فوق الصخور و الارجل مازالت ناعمة ما حفيت بعد…”</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Translation:&nbsp;“But there is a factor that resonates deeply within me, a factor that explains much of the failure of ambitions and dreams… This factor, in short, is that the plans are laid on rocks, but our feet are still tender, not yet calloused.”</li>
<li>Interpretation:&nbsp;This emphasizes the gap between grand plans and the lack of practical experience or the “hard knocks” that build resilience and skill.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>“إذا كان المرء ينام حتي تجهرك أشعة الحمرة في عينية و يبسط خوان الطعام كلما اشتهي ، ويخصص الأوقات الطويلة للقهوة و الشاي و العصائر و الفطائر ، ولا يسمح لنفسه بأن تتنازل عن أي فرصة فسحة أو مسامرات مع أصحابة ، و لا يستطيع كبح جماح تصفح الإنترنت أن يسرق ساعاته ، اذا كان المرء كذلك .. وما زال يرجو ان تتحقق يوما ما خططه العلمية و الدعوية و الإصلاحية ، فمثل هذا الشخص قد استأصل عقله ، و زرع بدلا منه مصباح علاء الدين”</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Translation:&nbsp;“If a person sleeps until the red rays of the sun glare in their eyes, lays out a feast whenever they desire, dedicates long periods to coffee, tea, juices, and pastries, never allows themselves to miss an opportunity for leisure or socializing with friends, and cannot restrain themselves from internet browsing stealing their hours—if a person is like this and still hopes that their scientific, religious, or reformist plans will one day be realized, then such a person has removed their mind and planted Aladdin’s lamp in its place.”</li>
<li>Interpretation:&nbsp;This strongly condemns a life of indulgence and procrastination, suggesting that those who wish to achieve great things must sacrifice leisure and work diligently. They cannot expect to magically fulfill ambitions like Aladdin with his lamp.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>“لا يستطاع العلم براحة الجسم”</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Translation:&nbsp;“Knowledge cannot be attained with bodily comfort.”</li>
<li>Interpretation:&nbsp;This is a concise statement emphasizing the necessity of effort and sacrifice in the pursuit of learning.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>“الكمالات كلها لا تنال إلا بحظ من المشقة و لا يعبر إليها إلا علي جسر من التعب”</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Translation:&nbsp;“All perfections are not achieved except through a portion of hardship, and they cannot be crossed except on a bridge of fatigue.”</li>
<li>Interpretation:&nbsp;This highlights that excellence and mastery require sustained effort, difficulty, and resilience.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>“تلمح فجر الأجر يهن ظلام التكليف”</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Translation:&nbsp;“You perceive the dawn of reward makes the darkness of duty pale.”</li>
<li>Interpretation:&nbsp;This suggests that the hope of reward and the meaningful impact of your work make the hard work and sacrifice worthwhile.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>“بقدر ما تتعني تنال ما تتمني”</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Translation:&nbsp;“To the extent that you exert yourself, to that extent you will achieve what you desire.”</li>
<li>Interpretation:&nbsp;This is a direct statement of the relationship between effort and achievement.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>“ولم تعطني الأيام نوما مسكنا ألذ به ، إلا بنوم مشرد”</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Translation:&nbsp;“The days have not given me a comforting sleep more delicious than a scattered one.”</li>
<li>Interpretation:&nbsp;This beautifully evokes the idea that true rest is often earned by hard work and might not always be the most comfortable.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>“و اذا كانت النفوس كبارا تعبت في مرادها الأجسام”</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Translation:&nbsp;“If the souls are great, the bodies will toil in pursuit of their desires.”</li>
<li>Interpretation:&nbsp;This highlights that ambitious goals require a commitment to hard work that will test the physical body.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>“وكذلك يحذر من التنقل من كتاب الي كتاب من غير موجب فإنه علامة الضجر وعدم الفلاح”</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Translation:&nbsp;“Likewise, he warns against moving from book to book without a valid reason, for it is a sign of boredom and lack of success.”</li>
<li>Interpretation:&nbsp;This advises against haphazardly abandoning study materials, highlighting that deep learning comes from thorough exploration.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>“وإن من الحكمة أن من ابتدأ بعمل وارتاح له فليستمر عليه ، فمن بورك له في شئ فليلزمه ، وبعض الناس يبدأ الأعمال و لا يتممها ، فيمضي عليه الوقت سبهللا من غير فائدة فمثلا يقراء في هذا الكتاب او هذا الفن ، ثم يدعه من غير ان يكمله وينتقل الي غيره ، ثم الي اخر ، من غير تكميل الأول فيضيع عمله وينقضي عمره بلا فائدة ، وكذلك في الأعمال الاخري كل يوم له عمل وكل عمل له راي فيضيع الوقت عليه من غير فائدة”</strong> - Translation:&nbsp;“And it is wisdom that whoever begins a work and finds comfort in it should continue with it. For whoever is blessed in something should stick to it. And some people begin tasks and do not complete them, so their time passes in vain without benefit. For example, they read in this book or this discipline and then leave it without completing it and move on to another and then another without completing the first, so they waste their work and their lives pass without benefit. And likewise in other works, each day has a work and each work has its own approach, so they waste time on that without benefit.”</p></li>
</ol>
<p>For opensource project i have a lot of coold projects that i strated and will start soon but didn’t complete any one yet and i know when i finish one i will get a job easly but this is what happend.</p>
</section>
<section id="imam-al-nawawi" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="imam-al-nawawi">Imam Al-Nawawi</h2>
<p>Al-Nawawi began his pursuit of knowledge relatively late, in the year 649 AH. He was, as he himself stated, 19 years old at that time. This was considered a late start compared to the custom of their time, where people would begin seeking knowledge before reaching puberty. As Al-Nawawi himself said, “When I was nineteen years old, my father brought me to Damascus in the year forty-nine, and I resided in the Rawahiyya School.”</p>
<p>Al-Nawawi, may God have mercy on him, passed away in the year 676 AH, at the age of 45. Scholars in their forties typically begin to produce their most refined and meticulously researched scholarly work. Thus, the Sheikh, may God have mercy on him, did not live long.</p>
<p>Well then… when did the Sheikh begin writing and authoring? The Sheikh himself stated that he spent six years in the pursuit of knowledge, and then began authoring, i.e., he began authoring at the age of 25.</p>
<p>Al-Nawawi also informed his student, Ibn al-Attar:</p>
<p>“He mentioned to me, may God have mercy on him, that he did not waste any time, night or day, except in a task of engaging with knowledge. Even while walking on the streets, he would engage in reviewing what he had memorized or studying. He remained engaged in acquiring knowledge in this manner for about six years, and then he began writing.”</p>
<p>This means that most of Al-Nawawi’s works that we circulate today were authored during his twenties and thirties!</p>
<p>Al-Isnawi explains: “This phenomenon with Sheikh Muhi al-Din al-Nawawi was quite common. It is that, when he became qualified to study and acquire knowledge, he saw that it was part of his striving towards good deeds to make what he acquired and understood into an authorship, from which the reader could benefit. Thus, he made his authoring a means of acquiring knowledge, and his acquiring knowledge a means of authoring. Without this, he would not have been able to produce the amount of authorship he did. He entered Damascus to study when he was eighteen years old, and died before he reached forty-six.”</p>
<p>Al-Isnawi’s point is that Al-Nawawi made his authoring a way to acquire and seek knowledge. He immediately put his seeking and acquiring of knowledge into the form of authorship, i.e., his notes during his pursuit of knowledge, he would convert them into a form of authorship, rather than allowing the notes of his youth to be wasted.</p>
<p>Was this a coincidence for Al-Nawawi, or was it a conscious behavior? Meaning, did Al-Nawawi keep in mind the benefit of authorship in educating the author himself? In fact, there is a statement of Al-Nawawi in his other book,&nbsp;Sharh al-Muhadhab, which reveals that his early attention to authorship was for the purposes of self-learning. In his introduction, where he explained the etiquette of a seeker of knowledge, Al-Nawawi stated:</p>
<p>“One should pay attention to ‘authoring’ when one is qualified for it, for through it one discovers the realities and subtleties of knowledge, and it becomes established in one’s mind. It forces one to engage in extensive searching, studying, investigating, and reviewing, and to become acquainted with the different opinions of the Imams, their agreements, what is clear, what is ambiguous, what is authentic, what is weak, what is eloquent, what is feeble, what is not subject to objection, and what is. Through this, a researcher takes on the qualities of a&nbsp;mujtahid&nbsp;(one who can exercise independent legal reasoning).”</p>
<p>Here, Al-Nawawi is not just encouraging authoring, but he is revealing the motivations that drive authoring and expands on the effect it has on the advancement of the student’s understanding by obliging them to delve deeply.</p>
<p>Also, Al-Khatib Al-Baghdadi said: “Whoever wants to benefit, let them break the pen of copying and take up the pen of research.”</p>
<hr>
<p>And I’ve noticed that a lot of prominent figures in Deep Learning (DL) are doing this. For example:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Michael Lanham</strong>&nbsp;(<a href="https://www.google.com/url?sa=E&amp;q=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.com%2Fstores%2Fauthor%2FB07BPS6WQL">https://www.amazon.com/stores/author/B07BPS6WQL</a>): The author of:</p>
<ul>
<li>Evolutionary Deep Learning</li>
<li>Practical AI on the Google Platform</li>
<li>Learn Python Game Development with ChatGPT</li>
<li>and many other books.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><p><strong>Christoph Molnar</strong>&nbsp;(<a href="https://www.google.com/url?sa=E&amp;q=https%3A%2F%2Fchristophm.github.io%2Finterpretable-ml-book%2F">https://christophm.github.io/interpretable-ml-book/</a>): The author of&nbsp;Interpretable Machine Learning.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Christopher M. Bishop</strong>&nbsp;(<a href="https://www.google.com/url?sa=E&amp;q=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.amazon.com%2Fstores%2FChristopher-M.-Bishop%2Fauthor%2FB001IGLMNY%3Fref%3Dap_rdr%26isDramIntegrated%3Dtrue%26shoppingPortalEnabled%3Dtrue%23">https://www.amazon.com/stores/Christopher-M.-Bishop/author/B001IGLMNY?ref=ap_rdr&amp;isDramIntegrated=true&amp;shoppingPortalEnabled=true#</a>): The author of the famous book,&nbsp;Pattern Recognition and Machine Learning. He once mentioned that he wrote this book to ensure his own understanding of these concepts.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>… and the list goes on.</p>
<p><strong>My Approach: Building, Not Just Reading</strong></p>
<p>I don’t necessarily aspire to write a book, but rather to&nbsp;recreate&nbsp;knowledge from the sources I’ve studied (books, courses, and papers). I don’t advocate for simply “writing a book” as a goal. Instead, I aim to create accessible pieces of knowledge that I can iterate on and use to help others understand these concepts.</p>
<p>This is my intended approach, and I will start with:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>“Building DL from Scratch” Series:</strong>&nbsp;Based on the fastai course and the&nbsp;Deep Learning from Scratch&nbsp;book.</li>
<li><strong>“Math Level Up for DL”:</strong>&nbsp;Based on multiple books, courses, and some experiments I want to conduct.</li>
</ol>
<p>Then, I will expand on these approaches in blog posts and other materials on topics like federated learning and other areas I’m interested in. I’ll try my best to do all of this effectively.</p>
</section>
<section id="not-just-the-math" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="not-just-the-math">NOT Just the Math</h2>
<p>This approach isn’t limited to math. It extends to every skill, including CSS, Deep Learning implementation with pure PyTorch code, and so on.</p>
<p>…to be continued.</p>
<p>you can read:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/fl/what_is_federated_learning.html">What is federated learning</a></li>
<li><a href="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/kamcalorie.html">kam calorie</a></li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>blogging</category>
  <category>ai</category>
  <category>math</category>
  <category>linear_algebra</category>
  <category>calculus</category>
  <category>statistics</category>
  <category>probability</category>
  <guid>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/math/math_skills_for_AI.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/math/images/Maslakiat.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>كم كالوري في الطعام ؟</title>
  <dc:creator>kareem </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/kamcalorie.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="كم-كالوري" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="كم-كالوري"><a href="https://www.kamcalorie.com/">كم كالوري</a></h2>
<p>موقع كم كالوري هو دليل القارئ العربي الي السعرات الحرارية في جميع الأطعمة بمختلف البلدان واللهجات ، دليلك لمعرفة القيمة الغذائية لها مثل السعرات الحرارية و المعادن ونسب البروتين و السكريات لحمية صحية و نظام غذائي أفضل تم إنشاء منصة كم كالوري بهدف توفيرمصدر موثوق و دقيق للقارئ العربي بتقنيات الذكاء الاصطناعي</p>
</section>
<section id="مميزات-الموقع" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="مميزات-الموقع">مميزات الموقع</h2>
<p>الموقع مبني بهدف تطبيقات تقنيات معالجة اللغات الطبيعية والنماذج اللغوية لتوفير كافة المعلومات التي قد يحتاجها الفرد مثل: 1. البحث الذكي : البحث باستخدام المعني سواء باللغة العربية أو الإنجيليزية وحتي كافة اللغات و يمكنك البحث باي طريقة سواء لغة عربية فصحية او العامية او حتي أخطاء إملائية 2. سرعة في إستراجاع المعلومات وعرضها في شكل بياني مميز يسمح لك بمعرفة المهم في وقت فوري 3. يمكنك إدخال ما أكل بشكل كامل و الموقع يقوم بحساب التقديرات اللازمة لك</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/images/kcal.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>كم كالوري</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="خاتمة" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="خاتمة">خاتمة</h2>
<p>يعتبر موقع كم كالوري بداية الي سلسلة ممن المنتجات التي تسهل علي الناطقين بالعربية ممارسة الرياضة و لعيش حياة أفضل و هناك الكثير قادم مثل : 1. كوب بروتين 2. عضلاتي</p>
<p>قام بتطوير و إنشاء الموقع عبد الكريم الخطيب باحث في علوم الذكاء الإصطناعي و مهتم باثراء المحتوي العربي</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>blogging</category>
  <category>idea_Forge</category>
  <category>publish</category>
  <category>rough_thoughts</category>
  <category>life_style</category>
  <guid>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/kamcalorie.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/images/kcal.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>أفضل أنواع الكرياتين مونوهيدرات و بروتيانات للتضخيم</title>
  <dc:creator>kareem </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/protienai.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>أفضل مساحيق الكرياتين والبروتين للتضخيم من موقع Proteinai</strong></p>
<p>هل تبحث عن أفضل مساحيق الكرياتين والبروتين لبناء العضلات وتحقيق نتائج مذهلة في التضخيم؟ موقع <a href="https://www.protienai.com">مساحيق كرياتين و بروتين لبناء العضلات والتضخيم</a> هو الوجهة المثالية التي توفر لك جميع الموارد والمعلومات اللازمة لاختيار المكملات الغذائية المناسبة لتحقيق أهدافك.</p>
<section id="ما-الذي-يجعل-موقع-proteinai-مميزا" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ما-الذي-يجعل-موقع-proteinai-مميزا"><strong>ما الذي يجعل موقع Proteinai مميزًا؟</strong></h2>
<section id="مراجعات-متخصصة-ومقارنات-شاملة" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="مراجعات-متخصصة-ومقارنات-شاملة"><strong>1. مراجعات متخصصة ومقارنات شاملة</strong></h3>
<p>يقدم موقع <a href="https://www.protienai.com">مساحيق كرياتين و بروتين لبناء العضلات والتضخيم</a> مراجعات دقيقة ومستقلة لأشهر مساحيق البروتين والكرياتين في السوق. من بين المنتجات التي يغطيها الموقع:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>ريدريكس بيج رامي لابس</strong></li>
<li><strong>Rival Nutrition - Rival Whey</strong></li>
<li><strong>MuscleTech - Nitro Tech Ripped</strong></li>
<li><strong>Dymatize - ISO100</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>تساعدك المراجعات على فهم المزايا والعيوب لكل منتج بناءً على السعر، المحتوى الغذائي، المكونات، والفعالية. بالإضافة إلى ذلك، يوفر الموقع خاصية المقارنات جنبًا إلى جنب لتحديد الأنسب.</p>
</section>
<section id="تصنيفات-مبسطة-لسهولة-الاختيار" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="تصنيفات-مبسطة-لسهولة-الاختيار"><strong>2. تصنيفات مبسطة لسهولة الاختيار</strong></h3>
<p>يسهّل الموقع عملية البحث من خلال تنظيم المنتجات ضمن فئات محددة تناسب احتياجاتك، مثل:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>بناء العضلات (التضخيم)</strong></li>
<li><strong>إنقاص الوزن (التنشيف)</strong></li>
<li><strong>التعافي العضلي</strong></li>
<li><strong>استبدال الوجبات</strong></li>
<li><strong>خالي من الغلوتين</strong></li>
<li><strong>نباتي</strong></li>
<li><strong>عضوي</strong></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="أدوات-وموارد-تعليمية" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="أدوات-وموارد-تعليمية"><strong>3. أدوات وموارد تعليمية</strong></h3>
<p>إلى جانب المراجعات والمقارنات، يقدم الموقع مجموعة من الأدوات والموارد لمساعدتك على اتخاذ قرارات مدروسة:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>دليل البروتين:</strong> يوفر معلومات شاملة حول أنواع البروتين المختلفة، فوائدها، ومتى يجب استخدامها.</li>
<li><strong>قاعدة المعرفة:</strong> تحتوي على شرح وافٍ للمكونات الشائعة في مساحيق البروتين والكرياتين.</li>
<li><strong>أحدث الأخبار والمقالات:</strong> تبقيك على اطلاع دائم بأحدث التطورات في مجال المكملات الغذائية.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="لماذا-تختار-proteinai" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="لماذا-تختار-proteinai"><strong>لماذا تختار Proteinai؟</strong></h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>شفافية كاملة:</strong> يقدم الموقع مراجعات دقيقة غير متحيزة.</li>
<li><strong>سهولة الاستخدام:</strong> تصميم بسيط وواجهة مستخدم مريحة.</li>
<li><strong>تنوع الخيارات:</strong> تغطية شاملة لأفضل المنتجات في السوق.</li>
</ol>
<p>استفد الآن من موقع <a href="https://www.protienai.com">مساحيق كرياتين و بروتين لبناء العضلات والتضخيم</a> لاختيار المكمل المثالي لتحقيق أهدافك الرياضية والصحية.</p>
<p>يمكنك استخدام موقع كم كالوري لمعرفة كافة السعرات الحرارية ايضا: 1. <a href="https://www.kamcalorie.com">كم كالوري بالذكاء الإصطناعي</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>blogging</category>
  <category>idea_Forge</category>
  <category>publish</category>
  <category>rough_thoughts</category>
  <category>life_style</category>
  <guid>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/protienai.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/images/proteinai.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What is Federated Learning</title>
  <link>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/fl/what_is_federated_learning.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>You’re on a mission to create the purest, sweetest, and healthiest honey in the world. As a mad scientist, you want to improve your beehive’s efficiency and ensure no one can steal your secret recipe for magic honey.<br>
After researching how to set up your beehive system—how the bees should communicate, and where to collect nectar in a protected way to guard against wasps that want to steal your honey and harm your beehive—you discover that a Federated Beehive could meet all your needs. However, it adds complexity to your system and requires a new mindset.</p>
<section id="traditional-ml-systems-centralized" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="traditional-ml-systems-centralized">Traditional ML Systems (Centralized)</h2>
<p>In centralized systems, you collect flowers into your beehive and start processing them to create honey, which is not secure since people will know the type of flower on its way.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/fl/images/centralized_learning.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>centralized Learning</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In centralized systems, we aggregate data from multiple sources into a specific center where training occurs, consuming significant bandwidth and moving user data off their devices.</p>
</section>
<section id="federated-learning-decentralized" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="federated-learning-decentralized">Federated Learning (Decentralized)</h2>
<p>In FL, your bees visit different types of flowers to collect nectar and bring it back to your beehive in a fast and efficient way. The nectar is covered in a protective container to prevent the scent from attracting dark wasps and others in the world. While this approach is secure and efficient, it requires more overhead in managing bee communication globally, combining diverse nectar, and handling potential issues like poisoned nectar that could harm your entire honey supply.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/fl/images/federate_learning.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>federated learning</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="introduction-to-federated-learning" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction-to-federated-learning">Introduction to Federated Learning</h2>
<p><strong>Definition:</strong> Federated Learning (FL) enables machine learning models on distributed data by moving the training to the data, instead of transferring data to the training center.</p>
<p>FL was first developed by Google in 2016 for their Gboard application, which uses a user’s typing history to suggest corrections and predict upcoming words while preserving user data privacy.</p>
<p>The idea is as follows: distribute our model across Android users’ applications, train their data locally on their phones, and then aggregate the knowledge each user has learned using aggregation algorithms like FedAvg to combine the updates into a single global model.</p>
<p>This process must be repeated for multiple rounds to allow the model to learn from these small updates.</p>
</section>
<section id="honey-with-multiple-flavors" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="honey-with-multiple-flavors">Honey with Multiple Flavors</h2>
<p>We decided to offer honey jars with multiple flavors based on the flower types from which nectar was collected. We’ll create a base flavor that everyone recognizes, plus special flavors with unique ingredients—some containing vitamin C, others a dose of caffeine.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/fl/images/multiple_honey_flavors.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Personalization in Federated Learning</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>In FL, this is called <strong>personalization</strong>. It can be seen as fine-tuning our global model (the base taste) with local data (special flowers) to meet specific needs.<br>
Since these unique flavors are likely to appeal only to certain local customers, they won’t be as popular with all customers compared to the base taste.</p>
<p>Our personalized model will excel on local data but may underperform on general data due to increased bias from fine-tuning.</p>
<p>An FL system allows us to manage the trade-off between user-specific preferences and generalization.</p>
</section>
<section id="horizontal-and-vertical-fl" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="horizontal-and-vertical-fl">Horizontal and Vertical FL</h2>
<p>There are two types of FL: Horizontal (homogeneous) FL and Vertical (heterogeneous) FL.</p>
<section id="horizontal-federated-learning" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="horizontal-federated-learning">Horizontal Federated Learning</h3>
<p>Imagine our bees extracting nectar from the same type of flower in different places and in various quantities.</p>
<p>An example of horizontal FL is the Gboard application, where local training on phones uses identical data formats with unique content reflecting the user’s typing history.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/fl/images/horizontal_fl.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Horizontal Federated Learning</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="vertical-federated-learning" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="vertical-federated-learning">Vertical Federated Learning</h3>
<p>For a new honey type, we instruct our bees to collect nectar from different plants with unique characteristics, creating a distinctive honey.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/fl/images/vertical_fl.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Vertical Federated Learning</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
</section>
<section id="why-fl-instead-of-centralized-machine-learning" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-fl-instead-of-centralized-machine-learning">Why FL instead of Centralized Machine Learning?</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Centralized Learning</strong> lacks security, making FL essential for industries like banking and healthcare.</li>
<li><strong>Private data</strong> availability surpasses public data, offering more insights and patterns to uncover new abilities.</li>
<li><strong>User preference:</strong> Some users expect that no data will leave their device. For example, entering passwords or credit card information should not send those details to a keyboard app’s server. This use case led to FL’s development.</li>
<li><strong>Regulations:</strong> Various data privacy laws (GDPR, CCPA, etc.) protect sensitive data from being transferred. Regulations may even prohibit organizations from merging their users’ data across different countries.</li>
<li><strong>Reduced Compute Costs:</strong> Centralized ML with large datasets demands high computational resources, limited by individual machine performance.</li>
<li><strong>Faster Training:</strong> With FL, models can train immediately after receiving data, providing users with faster, more responsive solutions.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="are-we-running-out-of-training-data-for-genai" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="are-we-running-out-of-training-data-for-genai">Are We Running Out of Training Data for GenAI?</h2>
<p>Most LLMs are trained on publicly available web data, but there’s a need for diverse data across modalities (text, images, audio, video). LLM architectures are similar, but the data they are trained or fine-tuned on is crucial. FL can help by enabling training on:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Private data
<ul>
<li>Phones</li>
<li>Emails</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Regulated data
<ul>
<li>Financial</li>
<li>Legal</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Sensitive data
<ul>
<li>Doorbell camera images</li>
<li>Medical</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Isolated data
<ul>
<li>Manufacturing</li>
<li>Automotive</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="wasps-attacking-your-data" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wasps-attacking-your-data">Wasps Attacking Your Data</h2>
<p>Federated Learning minimizes data exposure, but gaps in federated systems still need secure solutions.</p>
<section id="privacy-attacks-on-federated-systems" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="privacy-attacks-on-federated-systems">Privacy Attacks on Federated Systems</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Membership Inference Attack:</strong> Identifies whether specific data samples were used in training.</li>
<li><strong>Attribute Inference Attack:</strong> Infers unseen attributes of training data.</li>
<li><strong>Reconstruction Attack:</strong> Reconstructs specific training data samples.</li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/fl/images/privacy_attack.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Privacy Attacks on Federated Learning</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>We’ll explore different types of FL attacks and create defenses in a future blog post.</p>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h3>
<p>In upcoming posts, I will explain the components of Federated Learning in greater detail, including math, code, and more beekeeping analogies.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="https://flower.ai/docs/framework/tutorial-series-what-is-federated-learning.html#Challenges-of-classical-machine-learning">Flower Framework</a></li>
</ol>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>blogging</category>
  <category>publish</category>
  <category>fl</category>
  <guid>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/fl/what_is_federated_learning.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/fl/images/federate_learning.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="151" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Google Ads Black Box</title>
  <dc:creator>kareem </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/seo/google_ads_black_box.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="can-a-web-developer-creat-a-google-ad" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="can-a-web-developer-creat-a-google-ad">Can a web developer creat a google ad</h2>
<p>My cousin told me that he can’t create an ad for his work and he had a verified business profile, so i told him give you the website and i can do it in just few minutes. I opened google ads and created an account followed the instructions and added my visa then after one day the ad started to work.</p>
<p>Then i noticed that i want to change the ad to make it more advanced for mobile calls. I paused it and created a new one, then my account get suspended and the reason is because circumvengint systems policy! Okey, then what is the wrong? Submit an appeal and add the needed documents to get verfified and after 15 days there is no response and the account is still suspended, what about the money i give to the add and neither me or google is using it! It had fly with wind.</p>
</section>
<section id="another-try" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="another-try">Another try</h2>
<p>I toke my friend account, which is used for around 5 years on google ads and has spent a lot of money i create the ad with a different domain for the website and didn’t add the business profile and my identifiy is verified…etc my account get suspened immeditialy ? WTF!</p>
</section>
<section id="final-thoughts" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Dont’ add huge amount of money, add only 5$ with 5$ until everything is okey you can increase it abit for example 50$ per day.</li>
<li>Google Ads is a black box! What, why, when, how are irrelevant.: Go ahead and create a new account and do the advertiser verification before creating any campaign. You can try creating a new google ad account with same email ID first and same payment method. Google allows multiple ad accounts with single email. Yes I know they say that you cannot create new account but trust me they do not follow this. I have multiple stable accounts running under same email IDs which also have suspended accounts. Just get those ads live whatever it takes🥂 <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/googleads/comments/1fu5acv/suspended_account/">reddit answer</a></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/seo/how_i_use_nlp_for_seo.html">nlp for seo</a></li>
<li><a href="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/seo/the_curse_of_seo.html">seo if overated</a></li>
<li><a href="https://support.google.com/adspolicy/answer/2375414?hl=en">google help</a></li>
<li><a href="https://oudhmotors.com/">حجز موعد فحص المركبات بالدمام</a></li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>blogging</category>
  <category>publish</category>
  <category>google</category>
  <category>seo</category>
  <category>ads</category>
  <guid>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/seo/google_ads_black_box.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/seo" medium="image"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Learning Data Structures and Algorithms as Machine Learning Engineer</title>
  <dc:creator>kareem </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/ds_and_algo/master_ds.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="why-revisit-ds-and-algorithms" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-revisit-ds-and-algorithms">Why revisit DS and algorithms</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>I am a fresh graduate from AI college, i spent the last 4 years learning about both Computer science and AI.</p></li>
<li><p>I was learning some math, machine learning , Deep learning and a lot of programming with python and C++, spent some a lot of time learning web also for freelance jobs.</p></li>
<li><p>a lot of time i had multiple interviews while i was a student in the summer and all the time the questions was about linkedlist, and some medium leetcode question and a few of them was about frameworks like pytorch or pandas.</p></li>
<li><p>I faced a strange fact when i started to work on life projects or some advanced books…etc they require a strong problem solving skills that i don’t have!!</p></li>
<li><p>I am revisiting these topics and will try to get out from the juypter notebook and kaggle world in software engineer with python and focus more on open source projects.</p></li>
<li><p>I want to reazlie the time/memeory order of the data structures i am using in my projects</p></li>
<li><p>I have read the algorithm book v3 and spent 6 months on codeforces with c++ i remember these days where i could spent around 10 hours per day solving problems with myself before the AI assistants like GPT..etc i am missing the good feeling after every problem i manage to solve and i was able to write around 90 lines of code without research or AI help..etc.</p></li>
<li><p>I will start learning again about this topics and make them a daily habit to solve a problem per day: - <a href="https://www.manning.com/books/grokking-data-structures">[grokking_ds]</a> - it’s a new book about data structure in python and explained with the grokking style</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://www.udemy.com/course/python-ds-skills/">[DS with python]</a> - it’s a mostafa saad ibrhaim udemy course with python version with a lot of problems to solve</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://neetcode.io/roadmap">[neetcode]</a> - a roadmap to focus on some problems selected from neetcode</p></li>
<li><p><a href="https://codingchallenges.fyi/">[coding challenges]</a> - A SE problems to help you focus more on how to build projects not just problem solving which will help me to start doing some open source</p></li>
</ul>
<section id="times-i-needed-ds" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="times-i-needed-ds">times i needed DS</h3>
<pre><code>- multiple time when i was trying to building some solutions related to NLP or graph neural network i know that this problem must solved with Linkedlist and this needs a type of tree then i struggle to continue....
- Learning about some NLP Algorithms or the new searching and matching techniques most of the time they are math equations with some optimizations you can't fully understand unless your skills in problem solving
- research in DL needs a huge skills in problem solving and how to understand the following architectures then update or utilize them to your needs more in this in the future but i think the better you are in SE the better you are in ML.</code></pre>
</section>
<section id="topics" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="topics">Topics</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/ds_and_algo/Static_array.html">Arrays</a></li>
</ol>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/ds_and_algo/master_ds.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Review of Huawei watch gt 4</title>
  <dc:creator>kareem </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/products_reviews/Huawei_watch_gt_4_experience.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="buying-the-huawei-gt4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="buying-the-huawei-gt4">Buying the Huawei GT4</h2>
<ul>
<li>I bought it from Amazon for 13,000 EGP. I opened it immediately, and it looked so nice; I was very happy with its design and feel.</li>
<li>I charged it with the wireless stand.</li>
<li>I wore it after an hour and took some time to download the Huawei Health app on my Realme6 mobile.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="feeling-pain" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="feeling-pain">Feeling pain</h2>
<ul>
<li>I wore it, and after three days, my hand started to hurt, causing some discomfort because I was sleeping with it on without removing it.</li>
<li>I wore it on my right hand for four days, then switched it to my left hand, and my body felt more comfortable with it.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="the-design-of-the-huawei-watch-gt4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-design-of-the-huawei-watch-gt4">The Design of the Huawei watch gt4</h2>
<ul>
<li>The design is attractive, and many people who saw me wearing it didn’t notice that it was a smartwatch—they thought it was a classic watch.</li>
<li>Others said that it looks better than the repetitive and dull design of the Apple Watch.</li>
<li>It looks very premium.</li>
<li>The brightness in sunlight is impressive.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="sleeping-with-huawei-watch-gt4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sleeping-with-huawei-watch-gt4">Sleeping with Huawei watch gt4</h2>
<ul>
<li>The accuracy of the sleep detector is almost perfect. Sometimes, when you leave the watch near you for 6 hours, it detects that you are sleeping, but this has only happened maybe three times this year.</li>
<li>The accuracy of detecting sleep cycles and the time for each is spot on, and the graph analysis and statistics on this watch are easy to understand, creative, and full of information.</li>
<li>Why can’t I set an alarm based on the sleep cycle, like in the <a href="https://www.sleepcycle.com/">Sleep Cycle app</a>? This feature would be a game-changer!</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="calories-calculations-with-huawei-health" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="calories-calculations-with-huawei-health">Calories calculations with huawei health</h2>
<ul>
<li>You enter your information, like weight and height, and based on your vitals and activity, it detects the calories you burn every second. I like this estimation feature.</li>
<li>You can set a goal, for example, to go from 92 kg to 85 kg, but the problem is you need to calculate the calories and record it using the phone, not the watch. This is slow and inconvenient—I don’t like having to open my phone often. Most of the time, my meals are repetitive, and recording them on the Huawei Health app is boring, so I usually just do a quick add.</li>
<li>In the future, I hope they let us add a list of meals to the app so we can select them directly from the watch.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="activities-with-huawei-watch-gt4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="activities-with-huawei-watch-gt4">Activities with Huawei Watch gt4</h2>
<ul>
<li>Heart rate tracking is a little slow compared to real-time detection, and sometimes when you are running and want to check your speed and heart rate, it takes around 3 seconds—quite a long time if you’re in the middle of a run!</li>
<li>The auto-detection of activities may only start after 20 minutes of walking!</li>
<li>SpO2… and then what?</li>
<li>They claim there are more than 100 exercises to choose from, but do I really use all of these 100?</li>
<li>Let’s look at the ones that are useful to me:
<ul>
<li>Outdoor run</li>
<li>Elliptical</li>
<li><strong>Jump rope</strong>: My favorite! It’s accurate and very helpful.</li>
<li>Indoor run</li>
<li>Indoor walk</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Ones I don’t use:
<ul>
<li>Outdoor cycling</li>
<li>Indoor cycling</li>
<li>Pool swimming</li>
<li>Open-water swimming</li>
<li>Mountain hiking</li>
<li>Hiking</li>
<li>Trail running</li>
<li>Skiing</li>
<li>Snowboarding</li>
<li>Cross-country skiing</li>
<li>Triathlon</li>
<li>Rowing</li>
<li>Track running</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Are these really 100 exercises?</li>
<li>Where are the gym exercises like pull-ups, push-ups, squats, bench presses, etc.?</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="syncing-with-huawei-health" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="syncing-with-huawei-health">Syncing with huawei health</h2>
<ul>
<li>You must use one main device. I have both a Huawei Health and a Huawei MatePad, but I have to log in on just one of them to sync the information. What if I want to use both? You can’t.</li>
<li>Syncing with Linux or from the web? No, you can’t do that either.</li>
<li>However, syncing is very fast.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="messages-with-huawei-gt4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="messages-with-huawei-gt4">Messages with huawei gt4</h2>
<ul>
<li>I love the messaging feature. You can read messages in multiple languages without any problem and respond using preconfigured answers, but you can’t type on the watch.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="music-with-huawei-gt4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="music-with-huawei-gt4">Music with huawei gt4</h2>
<ul>
<li>The music quality and sound are great, especially if you want to listen to tracks before sleeping.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="calls-with-huawei-gt4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="calls-with-huawei-gt4">Calls with huawei gt4</h2>
<ul>
<li>Answering calls from the watch is really nice if you’re at home, but not so much if you’re outside on the street, for example.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="battery-with-huawei-gt4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="battery-with-huawei-gt4">Battery with huawei gt4</h2>
<ul>
<li>The best thing about the watch is the battery life. I don’t worry about it at all. I charge it for 30 minutes per week, and even when I use the always-on display, the battery doesn’t drain much.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="apps-with-huawei-gt4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="apps-with-huawei-gt4">Apps with huawei gt4</h2>
<ul>
<li>Camera Opus
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Photex
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Navigation - G maps
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>OneCalc
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>For Spotify Controller
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Calculator New
<ul>
<li>used it multiple times</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Events - G Calender
<ul>
<li>I use it alot</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Surfing Joe
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Mobcards
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>eSound music
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>petal maps
<ul>
<li>use it when walking and running</li>
</ul></li>
<li>navigation watch
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>easyCalenderGT
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>myTuner Radio
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>KeepStrong
<ul>
<li>The app has problem with login with google it’s focused more for Chinese people</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Compass navgation
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>TickTick
<ul>
<li>very useful can do/undo tasks from the watch but only tasks not the habbits</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Radarbot
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Fragola
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Salaat first
<ul>
<li>using it on daily basis</li>
</ul></li>
<li>home workout
<ul>
<li>not very useful</li>
</ul></li>
<li>2028 lite
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>wordpuz
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>love test
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>focus to-do
<ul>
<li>it’s not synced with cloud or the mobile app</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Dice
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Fitify workouts
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>RTL
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>hue essentials
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>FotMob
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Calories Counter
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>FilGoal
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>S7 Airlines
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>هسبريس
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Gold GPS Rangefinder
<ul>
<li>didn’t use it</li>
</ul></li>
<li></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="i-broked-the-glass-of-the-huawei-gt4" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="i-broked-the-glass-of-the-huawei-gt4">I broked the glass of the huawei gt4</h2>
<ul>
<li>The watch broke on the first day of college, probably because I pressed my hand too hard on a marble surface or something similar at the university.</li>
<li>I immediately contacted customer service, and a representative answered—I can’t remember her name—but she was incredibly polite, understanding, and helpful. I spoke to her again shortly after, and she asked me for specific information about the watch to check if it was under warranty or not. She followed up with me two days later, then again a day after that, and again two days later until I managed to get the invoice from Amazon. She tried to solve the issue by recommending an exchange and even told me which day to go when there would be discounts on the products.</li>
<li>Honestly, it was the best customer service experience I’ve ever had. She was able to go beyond being just a robot to become someone who understands, values, and helps—a human experience that brings joy.</li>
<li>At the very least, I had to document and acknowledge that she is someone exceptional. I requested to give her a rating, and I did. I’m really happy about that.</li>
<li>But I haven’t fixed the watch yet because there are no spare parts available in Egypt.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/products_reviews/images/back_gt4.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="sensors of huawei watch gt4"> <img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/products_reviews/images/broken_gt4.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="screen of huawei watch gt4"> <img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/products_reviews/images/gt4.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="review of huawei watch gt4"> <img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/products_reviews/images/face_gt4.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="face of the huawei watch gt4"></p>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/products_reviews/Huawei%20freebuds%205i.html">Huawei freebuds 5i review</a></li>
<li><a href="https://consumer.huawei.com/sa/wearables/watch-gt4/">Huawei watch gt4</a></li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>huawei</category>
  <category>watch</category>
  <category>exp</category>
  <category>blogging</category>
  <category>publish</category>
  <guid>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/products_reviews/Huawei_watch_gt_4_experience.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 03 Oct 2024 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/products_reviews/images/huawei-watch-gt4-14-day-battery-life.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="104" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The curse of SEO</title>
  <dc:creator>kareem </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/seo/the_curse_of_seo.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<ul>
<li><strong>Definition:</strong> SEO is optimizing your website pages to appear in the top results of search engines like Google and Bing.
<ul>
<li>Why is this important? It makes you visible to more people who are interested in what you provide—products, services, news, etc.</li>
<li>Enough of the basics. I assume you already know what SEO is about. Now, let’s explore a darker side of being involved in SEO.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>How to Track Your Changes</strong>
<ul>
<li>Since SEO revolves around ranking, how do you track your position?</li>
<li>There are multiple tools I enjoy using, such as:
<ul>
<li><strong>I love to manually search keywords and track their ranks myself! :)</strong>
<ul>
<li>I do this often when I need a break at the gym or during study breaks.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://www.semrush.com/">SEMrush</a>
<ul>
<li>I use it to check domain authority, organic keywords, and traffic increase.</li>
<li>Seeing green in increased Ref. Domains and Authority Score brings joy.</li>
<li><em>I don’t use it for anything else! :)</em></li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://rankmath.com/">Ranking Math</a>
<ul>
<li>Say hi to the overrated WordPress SEO plugin “Ranking Math SEO”</li>
<li>It claims to simplify content optimization with built-in suggestions based on widely-accepted practices.</li>
<li>I use Rankmath Pro on a website I manage, showing impressions, total keywords, average position, and clicks. GSC offers all this for free!</li>
<li>This post isn’t about Rankmath; that’s for another time. In short:
<ul>
<li>AI tools</li>
<li>AMP</li>
<li>Analysis from Google Analytics</li>
<li>Instant indexing</li>
<li>Backlinks count</li>
<li>Local SEO</li>
<li>News sitemap</li>
<li>Podcasts</li>
<li>Schema</li>
<li>SEO analysis</li>
<li>Sitemap</li>
<li>Video Sitemap</li>
<li>WooCommerce</li>
<li>Google Web Stories</li>
</ul></li>
<li>None of these significantly impact SEO and ranking; there are other effective methods.</li>
<li>What matters most to me with Rankmath is:
<ul>
<li>Top 5 performing posts</li>
<li>Other keywords</li>
</ul></li>
<li>I mainly use Rankmath for its focus keyword section in each article.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://mangools.com/">Mangools</a>
<ul>
<li>My preferred tool! Its UI/UX is excellent, and it’s fast and efficient unlike other tools.</li>
<li>With the free account, I get:
<ul>
<li>5 keyword researches daily</li>
<li>8 SERP checks</li>
<li>1,000 backlink analyses</li>
<li>Domain profile checks for 2 domains daily</li>
</ul></li>
<li>For Arabic, its keyword ideas aren’t as good.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://search.google.com/search-console/about">Google Search Console</a>
<ul>
<li>A free tool by Google offering most SEO tools’ functionalities for free and accurately.</li>
<li>You get:
<ul>
<li>Performance of your website for any keyword at any time in any region!</li>
<li>Page indexing status</li>
<li>Backlink analysis</li>
<li>Page experience and more</li>
</ul></li>
<li>You might notice a recurring theme:
<ul>
<li>Charts</li>
<li>Changing numbers everywhere, numbers galore!</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://app.neilpatel.com/">Neil Patel</a>
<ul>
<li>Rank tracking</li>
<li>SEO opportunities</li>
<li>Site audit</li>
<li>Keyword research</li>
<li>Traffic estimation</li>
<li>Backlinks</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://keywordtool.io/">Keyword Tool</a>
<ul>
<li>For Arabic, it provides the most related suggested keywords, though many aren’t quite relevant.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://www.guinrank.com/">GuinRank</a>
<ul>
<li>New and more tailored for Arabic, gaining power.</li>
<li>I use its content and keyword tools for Arabic, providing helpful recommendations and statistics for choosing useful keywords.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://moz.com/">Moz</a>
<ul>
<li>They even blocked my IP -__-</li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Starting to Lose!</strong>
<ul>
<li>What’s going wrong? I hate losing after investing time, money, and mental health into something. If you’re like me, SEO can be crushing.</li>
<li>“SEO is like gambling” ~ Kareem</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/seo/images/labtop_seo_increasing.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>How to recover form SEO addiction</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ul>
<li><strong>Losing Backlinks</strong>
<ul>
<li>Spam backlinks (like Khamsat, Fiverr, and Upwork)—most are harmful.</li>
<li><a href="https://khamsat.com/marketing/backlinks-building/2836532-%D8%AE%D8%B7%D8%A9-%D8%A8%D8%A7%D9%83-%D9%84%D9%8A%D9%86%D9%83-pbn-%D8%A7%D9%84%D8%A3%D9%81%D8%B6%D9%84-%D8%AD%D8%A7%D9%84%D9%8A%D8%A7">PBN Network</a>
<ul>
<li>This service claims safe PBNs for backlinks from Web 2.0 blogs, profiles, social bookmarking, social likes/shares, etc. I tried it, and none appeared in GSC after 3 months; worse, my site’s rank dropped.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><a href="https://khamsat.com/marketing/backlinks-building/2191705-%D8%AD%D8%B2%D9%85%D8%A9-%D8%A8%D8%A7%D9%83%D9%84%D9%8A%D9%86%D9%83-%D9%85%D8%AA%D9%83%D8%A7%D9%85%D9%84%D8%A9-%D9%84%D9%85%D9%88%D9%82%D8%B9%D9%83-%D8%B9%D9%84%D9%89-%D9%85%D9%88%D8%A7%D9%82%D8%B9-%D8%B9%D8%A7%D9%84%D9%8A%D8%A9-%D8%A7%D9%84%D8%AF%D9%88%D9%85%D9%8A%D9%86-%D8%A7%D8%AB%D9%88%D8%B1%D8%AA%D9%8A">Manually Added Backlinks</a>
<ul>
<li>This package offers 70 PR10 backlinks from foreign websites, 60 Arabic guest posts, and 10 EDU backlinks, etc.</li>
<li>It worked to some extent, but the impact was minimal. Four backlinks from specific places helped more than these services.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Other services are mostly spam backlinks; some guest posts might help, but aim for real backlinks spaced out from related sites.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Losing Ranking</strong>
<ul>
<li>This month, a home services website I manage improved from 65th to 9th in rankings, then disappeared, and later ranked 40th, etc.</li>
<li>This cycle repeats—a page gains rank, then drops.</li>
<li>It’s stressful; don’t check daily. Weekly (or every 2-3 weeks) is less stressful and gives fairer results, focusing on what’s important.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>What’s Going Wrong?</strong>
<ul>
<li>Watching page changes from these tools is like social media’s new “like” button!</li>
<li>My mind loves the green and red numbers.</li>
<li>Ultimately, most analyses aren’t critical. Whether 23rd or 80th, if not in the top 5, what’s the use? Daily checks yield nothing; reaching top 5 goes unnoticed until notifications and calls confirm it.</li>
<li>If SEO is your sole income source, it’s a tough job—even though it can make you a millionaire sometimes.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>How to Recover</strong>
<ul>
<li>Here’s what helped me recover from this addiction:</li>
<li>Create barriers for easy access:
<ol type="1">
<li>Separate Google accounts/tabs into another browser profile. Using Brave or Bing makes this easy.</li>
<li>Remove bookmarked tabs for these tools and clear browsing history.</li>
<li>Use extensions to block these sites; Chrome Store has many offering motivational quotes.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Delete Chrome and YouTube from mobile using <a href="https://askubuntu.com/questions/34702/how-do-i-set-up-android-adb">ADB</a>.</li>
<li>Move tool emails to spam except weekly updates from Mangools and GSC.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/seo/images/laptop_google.jpeg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>dark side of seo</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<ul>
<li><strong>Final Thoughts!</strong>
<ul>
<li>As a programmer, I initially thought a fast website and quality content were key in SEO. I later learned that choosing keywords and acquiring backlinks are crucial.</li>
<li>A nice Arabic book which will give you true information about SEO <a href="https://academy.hsoub.com/files/28-%D8%AF%D9%84%D9%8A%D9%84%D9%83-%D8%A5%D9%84%D9%89-%D8%AA%D8%AD%D8%B3%D9%8A%D9%86-%D9%85%D8%AD%D8%B1%D9%83%D8%A7%D8%AA-%D8%A7%D9%84%D8%A8%D8%AD%D8%AB-seo/">دليلك إلي تحسين محركات البحث</a></li>
<li>Feel free to DM on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/abdelkareem-elkhateb-989a68294/">Linkedin</a></li>
<li>Ultimately, backlinks boil down to how many you buy and from whom.</li>
<li><a href="https://anwan.me/">منصة صناعة المحتوي العربي</a></li>
<li><a href="https://oudhmotors.com/">شركة تنظيف منازل بالكويت</a></li>
<li><a href="https://el-harmeen.com/%D8%B4%D8%B1%D9%83%D8%A9-%D8%B9%D8%B2%D9%84-%D8%A7%D8%B3%D8%B7%D8%AD-%D8%A8%D8%A7%D9%84%D8%A7%D8%AD%D8%B3%D8%A7%D8%A1/">شركة عزل اسطح بالاحساء</a></li>
<li><a href="https://el-harmeen.com/%D8%B4%D8%B1%D9%83%D8%A9-%D8%B9%D8%B2%D9%84-%D8%A7%D8%B3%D8%B7%D8%AD-%D8%A8%D8%A7%D9%84%D9%82%D8%B7%D9%8A%D9%81/">شركة عزل اسطح بالقطيف</a></li>
<li><a href="https://el-harmeen.com/%D8%B4%D8%B1%D9%83%D8%A9-%D8%B9%D8%B2%D9%84-%D8%A7%D8%B3%D8%B7%D8%AD-%D8%A8%D8%A7%D9%84%D8%AC%D8%A8%D9%8A%D9%84/">شركة عزل اسطح بالجبيل</a></li>
<li><a href="https://kamcalorie.com">كم كالوري في الموز</a></li>
</ul></li>
</ul>



 ]]></description>
  <category>blogging</category>
  <category>seo</category>
  <guid>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/seo/the_curse_of_seo.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/seo/images/labtop.jpeg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>جاذبية مزيفة و عالم مخادع</title>
  <dc:creator>kareem </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/fake_graviety.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="البداية" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="البداية">البداية</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/images/burn_out.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>target</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>أحد الممارسات التي أقوم بها في بعض الأحيان هي مراقبة مصادر الأفكار التي تأتيني والمحفزات لها وتتبع أثر تلك الأفكار علي أفعالي ومشاعري ، يعتبرها البعض تفكير زائد وأعتبرها أنا نعمة تنقذني أحيانا من الإستغراف في الكثير من المهام والإستيقاظ متاخرا نسبيا.</p>
<p>بدأت المشكلة في الظهور في السنة الأولي الجامعية في تلك البداية التي يحاول كل شخص أن يظهر مهاراته وقدراته ويثبت نفسه ويحاول إثارة إعجاب الأخرين وتنشاءة العلاقات مع أناس من كافة المحافظات ذلك الدخول المفاجئ والكثيف كان له أثر نفسي سئ.</p>
<p>مثل تغير الاهتمامات علي المستوي الشخص والمعرفي و الدخول في تلك العلاقات الكثيره بدأت الأهداف المركزية التي كنت أحلم بها و أفكاري ومبادئ بالتشتت والتأثر بجاذبية كل شخص تعرفت عليه وصار بيني وبينه علاقة زمالة بل وحتي مجرد رؤية صفحته علي وسائل التواصل كل هذا طبيعي و مفهوم.</p>
<p>بعد محاول مراقبة الوقت اليومي واين يتم استنافزه وأين تسنزف أفكاري و مخزون التركيز لدي وجدت أني أذهب لنشر بيت الشعر هذا وتليخص الكتاب ذاك لأنتظر رد فعل فلان وعلان و انغماسي في الردود علي منشوراتهم وتتبع أخبارهم و تضخم طفيليي الفضول عندي بشكل مبالغ فيه مما أصبح يسبب قلق وحيرة وتشتت ومقارانات و وضياع أعمار.</p>
</section>
<section id="الإنبهار" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="الإنبهار">الإنبهار</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/images/effect_of_other_people.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>target</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>الإنبهار السريع باي شخص يتحدث عن شئ لا أعرفه مرت 6 شهور تقريبا وأنا متاثر ببعض الأشخاص الذين كنت أعتقد ان لديهم قدر من العلم والصدق والاشتراك في كورساتهم التي ستجعلني مبرمج لأحصل علي دخل بالدولار في نهاية الشهر القادم <strong>ذلك الشهر الذي أمتد 4 سنوات دراسية !!!</strong> شهر أسبوعه بمقدار عام!</p>
<p>لنرمز لتلك الفئة من المؤثرين بالرمز س وهو إختصار لكلمة سبوبة ينتشر هولاء الأشخاص في أماكن صيد المبتدائين يبيع لك هولاء الأشخاص الوعود البراقة كورس لتعلم السايبر سيكورتي في خلال 3 شهور أو تعلم دبلومة علم البيانات والذكاء الاصطناعي في شهرين تنبهر كثيرا بالكارزيما وطريقة الالقاء ونظافة المكان والمحتوي الذي يعد مبهر بالنسبة لك فلبس لديك أي آليات للحكم علي الشخص أو المحتوي فكل معرفتك في العلم هي تعال نجرب حصة عند أستاذ شكري</p>
<p>طالب لا حول له ولا قوة لا يعرف أي شئ في عقلة غير ملخص الدرس الذي يحفظة عن ظهر قلب ويذهب للامتحان ليسكب تلك الاسئلة الجاهزه في ورقة الامتحان الابله ليتفاجئ ذلك المسكين أن لا يوجد تعليم جامعي حقيقي وانها كانت كذبة العمر الضائع في كل تلك السنوات من الابتدائية وهو يسأل متي الراحة من هذا التلقين الفاشل وتكون الاجابة الكلاشكية هي أتعب الوقتي علشان تستريح بعدين بعدين امته!</p>
<p>في الجامعة عندما تنتهي من ال3 الثانوي لتصير دكتور مخ وأعصاب أو مهندس بترول</p>
</section>
<section id="الكهنة-و-المعبد" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="الكهنة-و-المعبد">الكهنة و المعبد</h2>
<p>سواء كانت نتيجة الثانوية مرضية و أرضيت والديك أم محزنة وأصابك اكتائب وامتلئت بالحزن فلا تبتأس فالقادم أسوء عليكما ومرحبا بك في عصر الكهنة الجامعية بعد مرات البحث العديدة وسماع الأراء هنا وهناك والكثير من الفيدوهات التي تذكر لك مميزات الجامعة الفلانية وأقسامها ونعيمها وتذكرك بالابتعاد عن الهندسة والجامعات التقليدية والذهاب الي كليات الجديدة مثل:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>كلية الملاحة والفضاء</li>
<li>كلية الثروة السمكية</li>
<li>والحبيبة الخبيثة كلية الذكاء الاصطناعي كلية المستقبل وصناعة الريموتات ومكن الخياطة</li>
<li>والكثير من الكليات الجديدة أو القسام ذات الأسماء البراقة “ليس عندي أي إعتراض عن أي كلية أو تخصص بل أتمني أن يكون عندي عمر لكل تخصص فشرف العلم كافي”</li>
</ol>
<p>لكن المشكلة في أنها مسرحية وسبوبة عامة وكل فرد مشارك فيها بداية من المدرسين والأهل و المهاطيل الجامعيين</p>
<p>ذلك المعبد الملئ بالالهة والكهنة والمحرمات والذي بمجرد دخولك لبوابة ذلك المعبد وتقديمك لأوراق الالتحاق فقد تمت عليك اللعنة الأبدية وكما دخلت جسد ممتلئ بالأمل أو حتي جسد ممتلئ بالحزن والندم فسرعا ما ستخرج جثة هامدة فاقدة الرغبة علي العيش بل تفقد في كثير من المرات إنسانتيك</p>
</section>
<section id="هيكلية-المعبد" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="هيكلية-المعبد">هيكلية المعبد</h2>
<p>بعدما قدرت علي النجاة ولحاق أي وسيلة مواصلات سواء من بيتك للجامعة أو للموقف العام او من موقف العام للجامعة هنيائا لك فقد استنفزت 20% من قدرتك علي الصمود</p>
<p>ستدخل هذا الصرح الهائل المبهر في بدايته وتتوجه الي المعبد الذي لعنت به الكثير من الخدم الأكبر منك يتنصلون للبحث عن الفتيات الساذجات لإشباع شهواتهم.</p>
</section>
<section id="الطاقة-السوداء" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="الطاقة-السوداء">الطاقة السوداء</h2>
<p>كان التفسير الوحيد لكل هذا العبث هو وجود خطة شر كبري من الفراعنة القدماء لتوليد أكبر قدر من الطاقة السلبية والإحباط في كل مكان يجتمع فيه البشر او كان يفترض ان يكون ولادة جديدة لأرواح متعبة.</p>
<p>يتم إستخدام تلك الطاقة وإمتصاصها فهي تعني لهم الخلود فتلك المنطقة حلت عليها لعنة لا يمكن حلها إلا بالقضاء علي الفراعنة و إعادة الارواح التي أغتصبت والأحلام المفقودة أحلام البسطاء وللحديث هنا بقية في مكان وزمان أخري.</p>
</section>
<section id="الجاذبية" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="الجاذبية">الجاذبية</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/images/graviety.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>target</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p><a href="https://ar.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D8%AC%D8%A7%D8%B0%D8%A8%D9%8A%D8%A9">الجاذبية</a> (من فعل جَذَبَ) وتعرف أيضاً باسم الثَقالة (من فعل ثَقُلَ) هي ظاهرة طبيعية يتم بواسطتها تحريك وانجذاب كل الأشياء من الكتلة أو الطاقة -بما في ذلك الكواكب والنجوم والمجرات وحتى الضوء- نحو بعضها البعض.</p>
<p>على الأرض، تعطي الجاذبية ثقلاً للأجسام المادية (الوزن)، وجاذبية القمر تسبب المد والجزر في المحيط. تسبب الانجذاب الجاذبي للمادة الغازية الأصلية الموجودة في الكون في البدء في الاندماج النووي، وتكوين النجوم -وتجميع النجوم معًا في مجرات- لذا فإن الجاذبية مسؤولة عن العديد من الهياكل الواسعة النطاق في الكون.</p>
<p>على الرغم من ذلك فإن آثار الجاذبية تصبح أضعف بشكل متزايد على الأشياء البعيدة.</p>
</section>
<section id="جاذبية-الأشياء" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="جاذبية-الأشياء">جاذبية الأشياء</h2>
<p>هل يمكنك أن تفكر كثيرا في كافة الأشياء التي تجذبك لها من حولك علي مستوي الوقت و الأفكار والمشاعر وقوة الإرادة!</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>تاثير أصدقائك عليك</li>
<li>مكان سكنك</li>
<li>أسرتك</li>
<li>وسائل التواصل</li>
</ol>
<p><strong>التركيز</strong> ليس هو قضاء أكثر وقت في أمر ما لكنه قدرتك علي إبعاد المشتات عن تلك المهمة والقدرة علي التركيز الكامل فيها. فمثلا: فمثلا التركيز هو ان تذاكر 4 ساعات برمجة فقط وليس ان تركز علي ساعتين برمجة ويب وساعة ماركتنيج وساعة مذاكرة للجامعة ومحاول التنقل بينهم علي= مدار اليوم او كما احب ان اقول علي مدار نوم!</p>
<hr>
<p>ليست القضية كم لدي من الوقت لأعمل كذا بل كم من هذا الوقت لدي القدرة علي عمل هذا فوجود 10 ساعات فراغ ليس معناه انك تستطيع إستخدامهم جميعا بل يوجد منهم مثلا 4 ساعات فقط وهذه رحلة طويلة وتحتاج لتنظيم عالي ومحاول وخطاء والكثير من النصائح ليس هذا وقت ذكرها.</p>
<p>فلهذا ينصح بالابتعاد عن وسائل التواصل و تدفق المعلومات التي تشغل عقلك وقلبك في بداية اليوم فبعد ساعتين تشعر بالصداع والرغبة علي النوم وكأن عقلك توقف عن العمل.</p>
</section>
<section id="حديث-تخرج" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="حديث-تخرج">حديث تخرج</h2>
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/images/chocies.png" class="img-fluid" alt="target"> مدي علي تخرجي من الجامعة بتقدير جيد جدا +B مترفع بضعة أيام تتملكني فرحة عارمة أنني قدت هربت من هذه السجون التي وضعت عليا طوالة هذه الأعوام شعور مريح جدا تبقي سجن الخدمة العسكرية اللهم إني أسالك الإعفاء من هذه التجربة ومن شرها وشر من فيها.</p>
<p>حديث تخرج في مدار جاذبية الأشياء السؤال الذي لم يتم تحديده بالكامل هو فيما سوف أتخصص الآن أفكر في إجابة منذ 3 سنوات وكل شهرين تزداد معرفتي وخبرتي وأجد أنني ليس لدي إجابة حقيقة حتي الآن. هناك 3 تخصصات أستطيع ان أبدا بها:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>مهندس برمجيات (ومن خلاله أختار فرع مثل برمجة الواجهات او الباك إند)</li>
<li>متخصص في علوم البيانات ( من خلاله أختار فرع مثل تعلم العميق والمجالات البحثية الشيقة الأخري)</li>
<li>الماركتينج + السيو + كتابة المحتوي (من خلال هو أقرب فرصة للحصول علي المال لسبب غير معلوم لن أصرح عنه) أين هي الصعوبة! الصعوبة تكمن في جاذبية كل فرع من تلك الفروع و أثر أختيار أحدهم عن الأخر من ناحية الأيجابيات والسلبيات لكلا منهما وليس هذا مكان النقاش ولكن ما أريد أن أشير له هو تأثير الإختيارات عليك و أثرها علي حياتك و وماهي أسباب ميولك الحقيقة لإختيار محدد.</li>
</ol>
<p>كيف سأختار الآن في الحقيقة قد أخرت ان أحجم جذب كل تخصص منهم لي في الفترة الحالية بالقدر الذي أرسمه لنفسي ومحاول الإلتزام بذلك والجمع بينهم للخروج بأفضل إستفادة ممكنة.</p>
</section>
<section id="جاذبية-المشاعر-الذاتية" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="جاذبية-المشاعر-الذاتية">جاذبية المشاعر الذاتية</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/images/groot.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>target</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>بعض الأمثلة التي أتذكرها و أجد فيها إستغراق أصحابها في كثير من الأوقات بغير قصد ونكران شديد لما يفعلون وهذا ما أخاف و أحاذر منه.</p>
<section id="الجيم" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="الجيم">الجيم</h3>
<p>في صباح اليوم دخل شخص أول مره أراه في الجيم يبدو متمرس في كمال الأجسام له نفسي عمري تقريبا يمشي مثل الحصان بشكل مريب تشعر كأن يريد أن يخبط في أي شئ أمامه ولديه إبتسامة عريضه طوال الوقت وعينيه تنظر لكل من حوله بشكل مريب وكأنه تقول هل تراني! أو هو كذا قرائها عقلي طوال الساعتين التي قضاهم بجانبي يصرخ بصوت عالي أعلي من روني كولمان بشكل مريب برغم أن الاثقال التي يتمرن بها قريبة جدا وأحيانا أقل من التي أتمرن بها و تعامله مع الأوزان غريب بحق يرفع البار الحديدي لأعلي ويسقطه علي الأرض بقوه ولديه هوس بالصراخ والتكسير حتي أن من يبعده دورين يستيطع سماعة ومن يسكن في الدور او يمشي في الشارع ونحن في الدور ال3 يستطيع سماعة بصوت واضح فياتري ماهو مصدر الجاذبية والمحرك لهذه الأفعال التي لم تستطيع كلماتي وصف الهمجية و الإزعاج المبتذل اليوم</p>
</section>
<section id="الجامعة" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="الجامعة">الجامعة</h3>
<p>يحضرني ذكر مثالين منتشرين طالب الإتحاد او الأنشطة الطالبية الكثيره</p>
<section id="إتحاد-الطلبة-والأنشطة-الطلابية" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="إتحاد-الطلبة-والأنشطة-الطلابية">إتحاد الطلبة والأنشطة الطلابية</h4>
<p>ذلك الطلاب صاحب البدلة الأنيقة والإبتسامة العريضة الذي يشغل نفسه في الإحتفالات والتنظيمات والممارسات الإجتماعية الكثير وتنظيم الندوات والكثير من هذا النفاق (أتحدث عن الواقع الجامعي لعام 2024) الأمر يشبه مسرحية سخيفة يصبح فيها هذا الطالب البائس يرقص علي هذا المسرح المزيف ويظن أنه بطل الفيلم وسوف ينتصر في النهاية ولكن كل المعتطيات تصرح بأنه مهرج بإمتياز ويخادع نفسه.</p>
</section>
<section id="أذكي-شخص-في-عالمه" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="أذكي-شخص-في-عالمه">أذكي شخص في عالمه</h4>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/images/fake_graviety.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>target</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>ذلك الزميل الذي تجدة يحاول بإستمرار أن يثبت لك أنه أذكي منك وأذكي من أي أحد في الغرفة وعلي بعد 100 كيلو متر من مركز وقوفه.</p>
<p>ذلك الزميل ينعمس في صوت الأيجو الذي بداخله فتجده ينعرف عن البوصلة الصحيحه لتحصيل العلم بشكل رأسي وأفقي بتوازن حقيقي ليصل الي مرحلة من إتقان العلم و الحصول علي وظيفة مريحة كم أشعر بالحزن عليه فلديه الكثير من الطاقة ولكنه يستغلها بشكل ربما يكون خاطئ و مؤكد أنه مزعج أيضا!</p>
<p>المؤسف انه بعد مرور بعد الوقت يبدا كل شخص منا في جمع معلومات في التخصص الذي يعجبه والإلتحاق بوظائف وصديقنا لا يزال في سراب أذكي شخص في العالم ومحاولاته المستمره بدون قصد لتبيان ذلك أصبحت مزعجة وأصبحت معرفته التي أكثرها أفقية مصدر إزعاج ونوع من أنواع التباهي المثير للشفقة والغضب أحيانا! يمكن التفكير في جاذبية الإيجو عليك وخداعك لنفسك في الحاليتن والتفصيل كثير وليس الغرض التعميم.</p>
<p><strong>مقترحات للخروج من هذا الفخ</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>راقب وقتك علي وسائل التواصل الأجتماعي وليس المقصد كم تجلس علي هذه المنصات ولكن أنظر الي تعلقياتك و منشوراتك ستجد أن أكثر شخص تتحدث عنه بشكل صريح أو خفي هو كم أنت عبقري وتفهم ما لايفهمه الأخرين! كم أنت ذكي! ستجدك متقوقع علي ذاتك!</p></li>
<li><p>الإنسحاب من مراقبة و أعين الناس و محاسبة النفس بشكل أكثر حزم و الأنسحاب هنا مقصود به وسائل التواصل و التجمعات التي تظهر فيه تلك الأفعال مثل مذاكرتك في نفس غرفة السكن الجامعي أمام أصدقائك و سؤالك المستمر للأخرين هل تعرف ماهي نظرية الهتوانا مطاطا ! و دعني أشرح لك كم صعوبة هذه النظرية وعبقريتها ..الخ</p></li>
<li><p>لا تترك إشارات للاخرين مثل الاهتمام الزائد بحالات الواتس والتيليجرام وإظهار المستمر لماذا تفعل مثل ديسكورد والأغاني التي تستمع لها</p></li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
<section id="هوس-الجمال" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="هوس-الجمال">هوس الجمال</h3>
<p>هوس الجمال تلك الفتاة التي كل إهتمامها هو جمالها والجمال والثروة والمال تجد أنه مهوسة بالجانب البصري عندها بشكل يجعلك تظنها ماكيت مخيف من الإنجذاب للماديات بشكل يطغي علي جمالها كأنثي يصل الأمر الي إلغاء الهالة المحيطة بها كأم أو زوجة أو فتاة عموما تشعر.</p>
<p>مشاهدة الإستغرام والتيك توك بشكل مكثف ومحاولة تقليد الترندات والمشاهير والإنغماس في أخبارهم… بعد مرور بعض الوقت تجد أنك امام فتاة لا تدري أي شئ عن كونها فتاة غير جسدها وجمالها حتي هذا يصل بشكل خاطئي.</p>
</section>
<section id="الإستغراق-السياسي-والمجاريات" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="الإستغراق-السياسي-والمجاريات">الإستغراق السياسي والمجاريات</h3>
<p>يكثر فخ الجاذبية هنا في الإستغراف السياسي لك كأب وتقصيرك في تربية أولادك او زيادة دخلك و سد رمق بيتك!</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="أين-المشكلة" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="أين-المشكلة">أين المشكلة؟</h2>
<p>المشكلة ليست في الأنجذاب لشئ فهذا مستحيل حدوثه لكن المشكلة هل أنا فعلا أسير في المدار الصحيح الذي يتفق مع الغاية الكبري بأفضل شكل ممكن وهل توجد محاولة التحسين المستمر أم أنك تتركها للظروف وتلعب دور المفعول به! هل فعلا بعد ذهاب العمر هل هذا هو ما كنت تود أنك أمضيت فيه عمرك! الخطر يكمن أن هذا كله يحدث من شد وجذب بدون أن تتدرك في أي فضاء صار قمرك.</p>
</section>
<section id="جاذبية-الحياة-علي-الأرض" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="جاذبية-الحياة-علي-الأرض">جاذبية الحياة علي الأرض</h2>
<p><strong>طعام الروح</strong> : كما أن الجسد له غذاءة فالجسد خلق من طين تجد أن روحك تثقل وتزداد جاذبية الدنيا وشهواتها لك و كذلك فروحك لها غذاء وهو الذكر فالذكر غذاء روحك كلما أكثرت منه ارتفعت روحك الي الأعلي وخفة جاذبية الأرض لك.</p>
<p><strong>الهدف الحقيقي</strong>: الهدف أن تدور في المدار الحقيقي والأمن ولا تغريك الممرات القصيرة السريعة التي تنحرف بك ييمين وييسار الهدف أن يكون سيرك الي المولي عزوجل وذلك لن يتم الإ بمعرفة ما يجذبك ويعبدك عن المسار وتجديد النية الدائم والتوجهة الي ربك. أحب ان اسميه إستعادة المركز وتعديل البوصلة و أكثر مكان أجد نفسه فيه هو إما في صلاة صادقة في جوف الليل مع دعاء مبتهل أو في صلاة جماعة مبكرة هادئة. في تلك الحظة تجد السكينة في قلبك وتهدئ كل العواصف. اللهم أعنا علي ذكرك وشكرك وطاعتك وحسن عبادتك.</p>
</section>
<section id="مغدارة-المدار" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="مغدارة-المدار">مغدارة المدار</h2>
<p>بعض الحلول التي مازالت محل البحث والتجربة.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>سل نفسك ماهو المحرك الحقيقي لهذا الفعل او المهمة الحالية وبأي نية أفعلها</li>
<li>ماهي المشاعر المحركة لهذا العمل ومن هو مصدرها هل هم الأهل أم فتاة أم كلمة قالها احد ما ونسي ما قال!</li>
<li>هل تستحق كل هذا الوقت والمجهود فهذا الرصيد من عمري الذي لا يعوض!</li>
<li>هل هي حقا تقع في باب أهم الأشياء التي يجب ان افعلها ام هي شواغل تعترض الطريق</li>
<li>متابعة الوقت بفعالية من التطبيقات المقترحة لهذا :
<ol type="1">
<li>ActionDash</li>
<li>ActivityWatch</li>
<li>Focus Todo</li>
</ol></li>
</ol>
<p>مقولة مميزة من “د/عبد الرحمن المسيري”</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>وفي الرياض تفرغت تماما للموسوعة ..، وكنت أحرر بابا أسبوعيا بعنوان “إسرائيليات معاصرة” في جريدة الرياض، ولكني لاحظت أن انشغالي بالحدث اليومي بدأ يقوض من رؤيتي البانورامية الموسوعية، التي تركز علي الثوابت، والتي تتطلب إيقاعا بطئيًا، واهتمامًا بموضوعات تاريخية وفلسفية وجوانب استراتجية ربما لا تكون لها علاقة بمشارة بالحدث اليومي، ولذا توقفت عن تحرير هذا الباب) المسيري رحلتي الفكرية صفحة 539</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I am thinking, then i am not here!</p>
</section>
<section id="النهاية" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="النهاية">النهاية</h2>
<p>هذه هي مجرد خواطر سريعة غير منسقة وقد تبدو متفرقه لفتي تعصف به الأفكار والمشاعر في فترة شديدة التقلب فلتدعوا له ولوالديه وجزاك الله كل الخير إن أكملت القراءة 😚😚</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>blogging</category>
  <category>idea_Forge</category>
  <category>publish</category>
  <category>rough_thoughts</category>
  <category>life_style</category>
  <guid>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/fake_graviety.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jul 2024 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/images/burn_out.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="144" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>My little Dragon “kobo”</title>
  <link>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/mteb_encoding/my_little_dargon.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="table-of-contents" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="table-of-contents">Table of contents</h2>
</section>
<section id="the-time-i-spend-with-kobo" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-time-i-spend-with-kobo">The time I spend with kobo</h2>
<p>I spend on average 8 hours on my laptop “kobo” doing a lot of programming, machine learning experiments and browsing many taps.</p>
<p>I don’t use my phone a lot on average 1 or 2 hours, so i wake up and go to see my little friend and start journaling, wirte my ideas, perparing my todo list.</p>
<p>I have been using it for 4 years now, and it was a nice period i love that it hasn’t broken till now, everything is working good even the battery can stand for the 2.5 hours in the battery life with a lot of memory and cpu usage</p>
<p>You can easily say that my laptop is now a part of me i can’t live without it any more my dairy, movies, work and college is depending on it</p>
</section>
<section id="who-is-kobo" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="who-is-kobo">Who is “Kobo”!</h2>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/mteb_encoding/dragon_2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Kobo</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="system-specifications" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="system-specifications">System Specifications</h3>
<p>My laptop is a Gfthin 95 core i7 9th gen, 16 GB RAM, 512GB SSD and GTX 1660 Ti, 120Hz screen</p>
<hr>
</section>
</section>
<section id="msi-vs-lenovo" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="msi-vs-lenovo">MSI vs Lenovo</h2>
<section id="msi-with-linux" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="msi-with-linux">MSI with Linux</h3>
<p>After buying it, it wasn’t configured with Windows, but was another DOS version so I had to install a Windows version on it. After 1 week I get a lot of errors on it with the external monitor and the WiFi stops working or is not configured. I tried every Hindi video about this problem and gave it to specialists to try it, but in vain, the problem happened again and again.</p>
<p><strong>The solution:</strong> It was my first year at a computer science college, so the geeky thing was to use Linux. After some search, I installed Ubuntu and then tried a lot of distros like Void Linux, but the one that I picked and still use is the amazing PopOS! which is based on Ubuntu but better than it!<br>
The WiFi problem doesn’t appear again! And for Nvidia graphics, it’s solved in PopOS! which has a command to install some drivers. And everything works smoothly</p>
</section>
<section id="the-cost-of-it" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-cost-of-it">The Cost of It!</h3>
<p>I bought it for the cost of 20,000 EGP, which at the time I bought it was $X, but now 20,000 EGP is worth $XX due to problems in my country.</p>
<p>Its cost at that time is really high for my budget and family, but I insisted on buying it because I knew it would stay with me for years, so I wanted a good one.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-i-decided-to-buy-it" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-i-decided-to-buy-it">How I Decided to Buy It!</h3>
<p>The phrase “Machine learning needs an Nvidia GPU” was dancing in my mind, so my main focus was on a nice GPU card in a laptop with a low budget. After some search, I found that the best choices are MSI or Lenovo, but the Lenovo version cost about 4000 EGP more than the MSI.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I tested the keyboard of the Lenovo, and every time I felt like I wanted to cut my fingers off</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It wasn’t available online, so I had to travel 3 hours to the store that sells it. It was a nice experience to buy something I wanted instead of a random gift from my father.</p>
<hr>
</section>
</section>
<section id="i-am-not-a-gamer" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="i-am-not-a-gamer">I Am Not a Gamer!</h2>
<p>I didn’t use it for gaming because I am not a gamer, but I used it heavily in programming and some machine learning and basic computer vision models, and it works so nicely!</p>
</section>
<section id="kobo-for-ml" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="kobo-for-ml">Kobo for ML</h2>
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/mteb_encoding/dragon_3.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Kobo"> Machine learning is a wide area, and you can use the GPU for 3 things:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Train a model from scratch</li>
<li>Fine-tune a model</li>
<li>Evaluate a model (inference)</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li><strong>Train</strong> a model from scratch was an ideal task for such a GPU, but I was doing it for multiple computer vision classification tasks, learning new architectures, trying to build…etc. For ML you don’t always need a GPU but for deep learning, which is a subset of ML that uses more connected layers (which means more computing power and memory needs), you do.</li>
<li><strong>Fine-tune</strong> a model is the case I used the most - I download a trained model and try to make it work better on my data. What you need here is enough GPU RAM - in my case it’s a 6GB card. This worked fine with computer vision algorithms and classic NLP models with less than 1 billion parameters. There’s no chance to try the LLAMAS models on such a card!</li>
<li><strong>Evaluate</strong> a model means to just load the model and not fine-tune it.</li>
</ul>
<p>I was fine with all the ML tasks I tried to do, unless I opened the door to large language models like the GPT family (ChatGPT for example). These models require a lot of memory and need a good graphics card like an RTX 30 or 40 series to test, and there’s no chance to train these models on any RTX card!</p>
<section id="why-not-just-use-the-cloud" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-not-just-use-the-cloud">Why Not Just Use the Cloud!</h3>
<p>There are two main solutions:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Kaggle
<ul>
<li>Kaggle has two GPU options, and I used it a lot, especially if the data was already hosted on Kaggle and was more than 10GB. Other than that, I downloaded a sample of the data and did my work on my own environment with CLI commands and VS Code configurations. This helped me a lot compared to just using the Kaggle editor, and it’s faster too! Sometimes the Kaggle kernel panics or just stops responding entirely!</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Colab
<ul>
<li>Colab restarts after 4 hours and your work can get lost, and lots of annoying things like that happen a lot.</li>
<li>You have to pay for the GPU version. You get a number of hours to try it out, and it’s faster than my GTX 1660 by a good margin.</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
<p>But I didn’t love these cloud solutions, and I found having my own local setup to be faster and more comfortable.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="kobo-for-web-development" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="kobo-for-web-development">Kobo for Web Development</h2>
<p>I sometimes work on web projects (Django and JavaScript frameworks, especially AstroJS). I never had any issues building and testing web projects - everything worked nicely and efficiently.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-battery-life" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-battery-life">The Battery Life</h2>
<p>The battery life can keep it working for 2.5 hours when the power is out if you switch to battery saver mode. I don’t think it could last more than 1 hour in normal mode! This is the laptop’s biggest issue. Sometimes it powers off even when fully charged if you do a lot of computation without plugging it in.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-heat" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-heat">The Heat</h2>
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/mteb_encoding/dragon_4.png" class="img-fluid" alt="target"> I didn’t find heat to be a problem or even the fan noise in most of my work. But sometimes when running a deep learning model, the fan noise is a bit loud and it does get really hot. For normal coding and browsing though, there are no issues and the cooling system is fast. Overall I didn’t find heat to be a major problem.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-keyboard" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-keyboard">The Keyboard</h2>
<p>The keyboard is very responsive and well configured with smooth clicks - no issues or sticky keys even though I have fat fingers!</p>
<p>I’ve been using this machine for 4 years and I write a lot. No broken keys have happened despite my clumsy fingers. I have a mechanical keyboard that I sometimes use, but I always miss the feel of the built-in keyboard. The red backlight is decent.</p>
</section>
<section id="finally" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="finally">Finally!</h2>
<p><img src="https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/mteb_encoding/draong_1.png" class="img-fluid" alt="Kobo_finally"> I just wanted to say that I love “Kobo” and I’ve spent nice times with it - some really difficult and others really happy. It’s been a loyal friend and something to rely on.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/mteb_encoding/my_little_dargon.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 31 Dec 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>After one year of using Huawei Mate 11 without google services</title>
  <dc:creator>kareem </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/products_reviews/Huawei_mate_pad_11.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="table-of-contents" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="table-of-contents">Table of contents</h2>
<p>Here is an expanded version of your blog post with some additional details:</p>
</section>
<section id="why-i-bought-it" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-i-bought-it">Why I bought it</h2>
<p>I purchased the Huawei tablet because I enjoy creative activities like drawing, taking notes, and reading books. I wished to have an iPad or premium tablet with a good stylus to fully explore my creative potential. My brother found an excellent deal on this Huawei tablet for around 60% off retail price and gifted it to me. I’m very thankful to him! <img src="https://consumer.huawei.com/content/dam/huawei-cbg-site/common/mkt/pdp/tablets/matepad-11-2023-new/images/kv/Huawei-matepad-11-inch-2023-kv@2x.webp" class="img-fluid"></p>
</section>
<section id="pros" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pros">Pros</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Excellent audio quality with quad speakers</li>
<li>Gorgeous 10.95-inch LCD display
<ul>
<li>2560x1600 resolution</li>
<li>120Hz refresh rate for smooth visuals</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Fast charging capabilities
<ul>
<li>Large 7250 mAh battery</li>
<li>Supports 22.5W fast wired charging</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Comfortable lightweight design, easy to use for long periods</li>
<li>Seamless integration with other Huawei devices like watches and earbuds</li>
<li>Responsive stylus with good palm rejection</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="cons" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="cons">Cons</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>Tablet gets hot with prolonged intensive use like drawing or taking notes. Quite annoying.</li>
<li>Battery life is decent but not enough to last a full day with heavy usage</li>
<li>Frequent ads in App Gallery and default music app are frustrating
<ul>
<li>Should not see ads just trying to open App Gallery</li>
<li>Default music app tries to push online streaming service with more ads</li>
</ul></li>
<li>Many apps spam notifications asking to reopen them. Very irritating.</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="using-huawei-devices-with-linux" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="using-huawei-devices-with-linux">Using Huawei Devices with Linux</h2>
<ul>
<li>File transfers require a cable, no wireless sharing</li>
<li>Must use third party apps like KDE Connect for notifications</li>
<li>Can’t develop custom themes or scripts due to lack of developer tools</li>
<li>Syncing to Linux with Syncthing is slow and buggy</li>
<li>Overall poor integration with Linux compared to Android/Windows</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="issues-with-google-services-on-huawei" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="issues-with-google-services-on-huawei">Issues with Google Services on Huawei</h2>
<section id="stylus-apps" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="stylus-apps">Stylus Apps</h3>
<ul>
<li><strong>Infinite Painter</strong> drawing app has broken stylus support and no pressure sensitivity</li>
<li><strong>NoteShelf</strong> note taking app can’t sync properly with cloud drives</li>
<li><strong>Nebo</strong> note taking app has subpar palm rejection and no Arabic language support</li>
<li><strong>Flexcil</strong> best ebook reader/annotator but lacks Google Drive integration</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="gbox-solution" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="gbox-solution">Gbox Solution</h3>
<ul>
<li>Provides access to YouTube, Maps and other Google apps</li>
<li>Available on App Gallery with native integration</li>
<li>Minimal battery drain</li>
<li>But lacks support for many Google services like Podcasts</li>
<li>Buggy syncing with Google Keep</li>
<li>Can’t leverage Google Drive within other apps</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="apk-pure" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="apk-pure">APK Pure</h3>
<ul>
<li>Apps sometimes fail to open, just black screen</li>
<li>Too many ads</li>
<li>Lacks reliability compared to Play Store</li>
</ul>
<p>Overall, while the Huawei tablet offers excellent hardware, the software experience is hampered by lack of Google services. This leads to janky third party solutions and poor integration with Linux systems. I still enjoy using the tablet but hope someday Huawei can properly resolve these issues.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references">references</h2>
<ul>
<li>https://www.noteshelf.net/</li>
<li>https://www.gboxlab.com/</li>
<li>https://www.infinitestudio.art/painter.php</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/products_reviews/Huawei_mate_pad_11.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Huawei Freebuds 5i review: is it the best budget earbuds for Huawei phone owner!</title>
  <dc:creator>kareem </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/products_reviews/Huawei freebuds 5i.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="table-of-contents" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="table-of-contents">Table of contents</h2>
</section>
<section id="intro" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="intro">Intro</h2>
<p>Hi, In this fast blog i will talk about my review with Huawei Freebuds 5i, which is the first noise-cancelling earbuds i have tried. This is not an ad or even affiliate product, it’s my own review for fun and just seeking of knowledge. <img src="https://consumer.huawei.com/content/dam/huawei-cbg-site/common/mkt/pdp/headphones/freebuds5i/imges/huawei-freebuds-5i-kv.jpg" class="img-fluid" alt="freebuds"></p>
</section>
<section id="who-am-i" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="who-am-i">Who am i !</h2>
<ul>
<li>I am Kareem, a college student interested in machine learning and web technology.</li>
<li>I enjoy working deeply and seeking out quiet places, but I live in an area with some noisy disturbances in the mornings - people walking down the street, kids playing around the house, street vendors - which often interrupt my focus and break my state of flow.</li>
<li>I wish there was a solution to block out all these sounds so I could live in an isolated place free of annoying noises! Using noise-cancelling headphones or heading into outer space would be ideal environments with no bothersome sounds around.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="how-i-bought-it" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-i-bought-it">how i bought it</h2>
<ul>
<li>I bought it from amazon prime, and it cost me around 100$ or 3,200 pounds. It reached within two days.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="first-impressions" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="first-impressions">First impressions</h2>
<ul>
<li>Upon unboxing and using it for the first time, I was genuinely pleased with the initial track I played.</li>
<li>The sound quality was noticeably superior compared to my phone or any other earbuds I’ve previously used. I then tested the noise-cancelling feature and was amazed when I couldn’t hear my younger brother calling me.</li>
<li>The street noises were effectively blocked out, with only a faint hum reaching my ears, which was quite tolerable. Initially, the earbud tips were a bit uncomfortable, but after switching to a smaller size, the discomfort was resolved. Everything seemed perfect, except for a slight pressure in my ears when using the noise-cancelling feature, particularly noticeable the following morning. Despite this, my ears seem to crave the earbuds and my skin seems to miss them when they’re not in use. This can be a bit of a downside, but it’s not always the case.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="is-noise-cancelling-actually-work" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="is-noise-cancelling-actually-work">Is noise cancelling actually work ?</h2>
<p>I’ve used these earbuds in various settings:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Subway: The noise-cancelling feature combined with my music created an immersive experience, effectively blocking out any other sounds and allowing me to enjoy my tunes in peace.</p></li>
<li><p>College: Amidst the chatter and shouts of other students, I was able to retreat into my own world of sound.</p></li>
<li><p>Bus: The noise of the bus engine was successfully blocked out, but I could still hear the conversations of those sitting next to me. It wasn’t overly bothersome, but it didn’t provide complete isolation.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>In summary, the noise-cancelling feature works well, but it doesn’t provide absolute silence. I can still hear some ambient sounds. One noticeable issue is that when I make calls using the earbuds, I can hear the other person clearly, but they often complain about the clarity of my voice. They say it sounds distant and unclear, sometimes even asking to call back later. This issue is particularly prevalent when I’m on the bus.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-modes-of-the-freebuds-and" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-modes-of-the-freebuds-and">the modes of the Freebuds and</h2>
<p>Here is a rephrased version of the key points about the Huawei Freebuds 5i’s features:</p>
<p><strong>Noise Cancellation Modes:</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Noise Cancelling Mode</strong>: Actively cancels out ambient noise. Uses more battery power.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Off Mode</strong>: No active noise cancellation, but still provides some passive noise isolation. Less battery usage.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Awareness Mode</strong>: Allows ambient sounds to be heard clearly. Useful for hearing announcements at the gym or people talking to you. However, my own voice sounds muted in this mode, so I have to remove the earbuds temporarily to hold conversations.</p></li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Sound Quality Presets:</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><em>Default</em>: No sound enhancements applied.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Treble Boost</em>: Boosts treble frequencies. I haven’t used this.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Bass Boost</em>: Emphasizes bass when listening to music like hip-hop.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Voices</em>: Optimizes sound for speech clarity. I use this for podcasts.</p></li>
</ol>
<p><strong>Connection Priority Modes:</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>Balance Mode</strong>: Balances audio quality and connection stability.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>Sound Quality Priority</strong>: Prioritizes sound quality over connectivity. Uses more power which may cause occasional lag.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>I have not noticed any discernible difference between these two modes, so I just use the Balance mode.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-gestures" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-gestures">The Gestures</h2>
<p>The Huawei Freebuds 5i offer various gesture controls:</p>
<ul>
<li>Double-tap, Triple-tap, Press &amp; hold, Swipe</li>
</ul>
<p>I particularly enjoy the swipe gesture for volume control, as it works smoothly. The press and hold gesture is a bit slow, and the triple-tap gesture can be annoying since tapping your ear three times isn’t very comfortable.</p>
<p>Occasionally, the Freebuds don’t recognize when I’ve inserted the left or right earbud, and I continue listening with just one earbud without realizing the other isn’t connected. This doesn’t happen often, though.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-compatibility-with-other-devices" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-compatibility-with-other-devices">The compatibility with other devices</h2>
<ul>
<li>I love how it connect with both the phone and tablet without any problems or conflict</li>
<li>I’ve been using the Freebuds with my Realme phone, MSI Linux laptop, and Huawei Mate Pad 11.</li>
<li>The connection with the Realme phone is seamless, regardless of whether the AI Life application is used or not.</li>
<li>When it comes to the Huawei Mate Pad 11, there’s a feature that allows you to adjust settings directly from the Bluetooth menu. This is a functionality that isn’t available on standard Android devices without the AI Life app.</li>
</ul>
<section id="linux-connection" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="linux-connection">Linux connection</h3>
<p>I’ve connected the Freebuds to my Linux laptop using the ‘<a href="https://smarttech101.com/bluetoothctl-management-of-bluetooth-devices-in-linux/">bluetoothctl</a>’ command. However, I’ve encountered an issue where I need to restart Bluetooth each time I want to establish a connection for it to work properly</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="the-case-and-overall-design" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-case-and-overall-design">The case and overall design</h2>
<ul>
<li>The design of the Freebuds is truly appealing. It has a unique aesthetic that sets it apart from other earbuds, giving it a premium feel.</li>
<li>In terms of design, the FreeBuds 5i bear a resemblance to the 4i model, but they are 11% lighter and have shorter stems. They come with an IP54 rating, making them dust-tight and splash-resistant. The color options include a new “Isle Blue”, along with “Nebula Black” and “Ceramic White”. The package includes small, medium, and large silicone eartips, as well as a short USB-C cable for charging the case.</li>
<li>I love the sound of closing it, it’s a loud sound but lovely :)</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="the-battery" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-battery">The battery</h2>
<ul>
<li>The battery is really nice; I haven’t felt that I am missing the need to recharge it or that it has gone off at any time.</li>
</ul>
<section id="battery-capacity" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="battery-capacity">Battery capacity</h3>
<ul>
<li>Per earbud: 55 mAh (min)*</li>
<li>Charging case: 410 mAh (min)*</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="playtime" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="playtime">Playtime</h3>
<ul>
<li>Music playback on 1 charge: 6.0 hours (with ANC enabled)**</li>
<li>Music playback on 1 charge: 7.5 hours (with ANC disabled)**</li>
<li>Music playback with charging case: 18.5 hours (with ANC enabled)**</li>
<li>Music playback with charging case: 28 hours (with ANC disabled)**</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="charging-time" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="charging-time">Charging Time</h3>
<ul>
<li>About 60 minutes for the earbuds (in the charging case)***</li>
<li>About 110 for charging case without earbuds (wired)***</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h2>
<ul>
<li>https://smarttech101.com/bluetoothctl-management-of-bluetooth-devices-in-linux/</li>
<li>https://askubuntu.com/questions/1225896/huawei-freebuds-3-pairing-with-ubuntu-18-04</li>
<li><a href="https://kamcalorie.com">كم كالوري</a></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/products_reviews/Huawei freebuds 5i.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>MTEB Massive Text Embedding Benchmark</title>
  <link>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/mteb_encoding/MTEB_massive_text_embedding_benchmark.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="introduction" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>#defintion MTEB: MTEB spans 8 embedding tasks covering a total of 58 datasets and 112 languages. Through the benchmarking of 33 models on MTEB.</p>
</section>
<section id="embedding-models" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="embedding-models">Embedding models</h2>
<ul>
<li>Text embedding models like GLove lack context awareness and ar=e thus commonly labeled as word embedding model. They consist of a layer mapping each input word to a vector often followed by an averaging layer to provide a final embedding invariant of input length.</li>
<li>Transformers inject context awareness into language models via self-attention and form the foundation of most recent embedding models.
<ul>
<li>BERT uses the transformer architecture and performs large-scale self-supervised pre-training. The resulting model can directly be used to produce text embeddings via an averaging operation alike Glove.</li>
<li>SBERT be beneficial to perform additional fine-tuning of the transformer for competitive embedding performance.</li>
<li><em>Most recent fine-tuned embedding models use a contrastive loss objective to perform supervised fine-tuned on positive and negative text pairs</em></li>
<li>#critique Due to the large variety of available pretrained transformers,there is an at least equally large variety of potential text embedding models to be explored.This leads to confusion about which model provides practitioners with the best performance for their embedding use case.</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="the-problem" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-problem">The problem</h2>
<ul>
<li>The problem with the current evaluation regime of current text embedding models rarely covers the breadth of their possible use cases.
<ul>
<li>#example SimCSE or SBERT solely evaluate on STS and classification tasks,leaving open questions about the transfer ability of the embedding models to search or clustering tasks.</li>
</ul></li>
<li>evaluating embedding methods on many tasks requires implementing multiple evaluation pipelines.</li>
<li>implementation details like preprocessing or hyperparameters may influence the results making it unclear whether performance improvements simply come from a favorable evaluation pipeline. This leads to the “blind” application of these models to new use cases in industry or requires incremental work to reevaluate them on different tasks.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="the-solution-with-this-benchmark" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-solution-with-this-benchmark">The solution with this benchmark</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>MTEB</strong> consists of 58 datasets covering 112 languages from 8 embedding tasks:</li>
</ul>
<ol type="1">
<li>Bitext mining</li>
<li>classification</li>
<li>clustering</li>
<li>pair classification</li>
<li>reranking, retrieval</li>
<li>STS</li>
<li>summarization.</li>
</ol>
<ul>
<li>MTEB software is available open-source1 enabling evaluation of any embedding model by adding less than 10 lines of code.</li>
<li>Datasets and the MTEB leaderboard are available on the Hugging Face Hub2 .</li>
<li>We evaluate over 30 models on MTEB with additional speed and memory benchmarking to provide a holistic view of the state of text embedding models. We cover both models available open-source as well as models accessible via APIs, such as the OpenAI Embeddings endpoint</li>
<li>It aims to sheds light on the weaknesses and strenghts of individual models,such as SimCSE’s<a href="https://doi.org/10.48550/ARXIV.2004.07180">(Gao et al., 2021b)</a> low performance on clustering and retrieval despite its strong performance on STS.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="the-mteb-desiderata" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-mteb-desiderata">The MTEB Desiderata</h2>
<p>METB is build on a set of desiderat.</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><strong>Diversity</strong>:
<ul>
<li>it consists of 58 total datasets, 10 are multilingual, covering 112 different langauges.</li>
<li>Sentence-level and paragraph level datasets are included to contrast performance on short and long texts.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Simplicity</strong>
<ul>
<li>It provides a simple API for plugging in any model that given a list of text can produce a vector for each list of texts can produce a vector for each list item with a consistent shape.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Extensibility</strong>
<ul>
<li>you can add new datasets for existing tasks via a single file that specifies the task and a Huggingface dataset name where the data has been uploaded.</li>
<li>New tasks require implementing a task interface for loading the data and an evaluator for benchmarking</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Reproduciblity</strong>
<ul>
<li>Through versioning at a dataset and software level,they make it easy to reproduce results in METP.</li>
<li>JSON files corresponding to all results available in this paper have been made available together with the MTEB benchmark</li>
</ul></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="tasks-and-evaluation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="tasks-and-evaluation">Tasks and Evaluation</h2>
<p>#definition <strong>Bitext Mining</strong><br>
Inputs are two sets of sentences from two different languages. For each sentence in the first set, the best match in the second set needs to be found.</p>
<ul>
<li>The matches are commonly translations.</li>
<li>The Provided model i used to embed each sentence and the closest pairs are found via cosine similarity</li>
<li>F1 serves as the main metric for bitext mining.Accuracy, precision and recall are also computed. #definition <strong>Classification</strong></li>
<li>A train and test set are embedded with the provided model.</li>
<li>The train set embeddings are used to train a logistic regression classifier with 100 maximum iterations, which is scored on the test set.</li>
<li>The main metric is accuracy with average precision and f1 additionally provided. #definition <strong>Clustering</strong> Given a set of sentences or paragraphs, the goal is to group them into meaningful clusters.</li>
<li>A mini-batch k-means model with batch size 32 and k equal to the number of different labels is trained on the embedded texts.</li>
<li>The model scored using V-measure - V-measure does not depend on the cluster label,thus the permutation of labels does not affect the score. #definition <strong>Classification</strong> A pair of text inputs is provided and a label needs to be assigned. Labels are typically binary variables denoting duplicate or paraphrase pairs.</li>
<li>The two texts are embedded and their distance is computed with various metrics (cosine similarity, dot product, euclidean distance, manhattan distance).</li>
<li>Using the best binary thresh- old accuracy, average precision, f1, precision and recall are computed.</li>
<li>The average precision score based on cosine similarity is the main metric. #definition <strong>Reranking</strong> : Inputs are a query and a list of relevant and irrelevant reference texts. The aim is to rank the results according to their relevance to the query.</li>
<li>The model is used to embed the references which are then compared to the query using cosine similarity.</li>
<li>The resulting ranking is scored for each query and averaged across all queries.</li>
<li>Metrics are mean MRR@k and MAP with the latter being the main metric. #definition <strong>Retrieval</strong> Each dataset consists of a corpus, queries and a mapping for each query to relevant documents from the corpus.</li>
<li>The aim is to find these relevant documents.</li>
<li>The provided model is used to embed all queries and all corpus documents and similarity scores are computed using cosine similarity. After ranking the corpus documents for each query based on the scores, nDCG@k, MRR@k, MAP@k, precision@k and recall@k are computed for several values of k. nDCG@10 serves as the main metric.</li>
<li>MTEB reuses datasets and evaluation from BEIR (Thakur et al., 2021). #definition <strong>Semantic Textual Similarity (STS)</strong> Given a sentence pair the aim is to determine their similarity. Labels are continuous scores with higher numbers indicating more similar sentences.</li>
<li>The provided model is used to embed the sentences and their similarity is computed using various distance metrics.</li>
<li>Distances are benchmarked with ground truth similarities using Pearson and Spearman correlations.</li>
<li>Spearman correlation based on cosine similarity serves as the main metric (Reimers et al.,2016). #definition <strong>Summarization</strong> A set of human-written and machine-generated summaries are provided. The aim is to score the machine summaries. The provided model is first used to embed all summaries. For each machine summary embedding, distances to all human summary embeddings are computed. The closest score (e.g.&nbsp;highest cosine similarity) is kept and used as the model’s score of a single machine-generated summary. Pearson and Spearman correlations with ground truth human assessments of the machine-generated summaries are computed. Like for STS, Spearman correlation based on cosine similarity serves as the main metric</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>#sidenote <strong>Non-Transformers</strong> : LASER (Heffernan et al.,2022) is the only context aware non-transformer model we benchmark, relying on an LSTM (Hochreiter and Schmidhuber, 1997) instead. Similar to LaBSE, the model trains on parallel data and focuses on bitext mining applications. ![[Pasted image 20231028124555.png]]</p>
</section>
<section id="analysis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="analysis">Analysis</h2>
<ul>
<li>we observe that there is considerable variability between tasks. No model claims the state-of-the-art in all seven English tasks.</li>
<li>There is even more variability in the results per dataset present in the appendix.</li>
<li>Further, there remains a large gap between self-supervised and supervised methods.</li>
<li>Self-supervised large language models have been able to close this gap in many natural language generation tasks (Chowd- hery et al., 2022).</li>
<li>However, they appear to still require supervised fine-tuning for competitive em- bedding performance.</li>
<li>We find that performance strongly coorelates with model size, A majority of MTEB tasks are domainted by multi-billion parameter models.However, these come at a significant cost</li>
<li><strong>For classification</strong>
<ul>
<li>ST5 models dominate the classification task across most datasets</li>
<li>ST5-XXL has the highest average performance, 3% ahead of the best non-ST5 model, OpenAI Ada Similarity</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Clustering</strong>
<ul>
<li>Despite being almost 50x smaller, the MPNet embedding model is on par with the ST5- XXL state-of-the-art on Clustering. This may be due to the large variety of datasets MPNet (and MiniLM) has been fine-tuned on.</li>
<li>Clustering requires coherent distances between a large number of embeddings.</li>
<li>Models like SimCSE-sup or SGPTnli, which are only fine-tuned on a single dataset,NLI, may produce incoherent embeddings when encountering topics unseen during fine-tuning.</li>
<li>Relatedly, we find that the query embeddings of SGPT-msmarco and the Ada Search endpoint are competitive with SGPT-nli and the Ada Similarity endpoint,respectively.</li>
<li>We refer to the public leaderboard5 for Ada Search results. This could be due to the MSMARCO dataset being significantly larger than NLI.</li>
<li>Thus, while the OpenAI docs recommend using the similarity embeddings for clustering use cases6 , the retrieval query embeddings may be the better choice in some cases.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Pair Classification</strong>
<ul>
<li>GTR-XL and GTR-XXL have the strongest performance. Pair classification is closest to STS in its framing, yet models rank significantly differently on the two tasks. This highlights the importance of benchmarking on a diverse set of tasks to avoid blindly reusing a model for a different task.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Reranking</strong>
<ul>
<li>MPNet and MiniLM models perform strongly on reranking tasks.</li>
<li>On SciDocsRR (Co-han et al., 2020a) they perform far better than big- ger models, which is likely due to parts of SciDocsRR being included in their training data.</li>
<li>Our scale of experiments and that of model pre-training make controlling for data contamination challenging.</li>
<li>Thus, we ignore overlap of MTEB datasets with model training datasets in MTEB scores.</li>
<li>As long as enough datasets are averaged, we believe these effects to be insignificant.</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>Retrieval</strong>
<ul>
<li>SGPT-5.8B-msmarco is the best em- bedding model on the BEIR subset in MTEB as well as on the full BEIR benchmark (Thakur et al., 2021; Muennighoff, 2022).</li>
<li>The even larger 7.1B SGPT model making use of BLOOM (Scao et al., 2022) performs significantly weaker, which is likely due to the multilinguality of BLOOM.</li>
<li>Models geared towards STS (SimCSE, ST5, SGPT- nli) perform badly on retrieval tasks.</li>
<li>Retrieval tasks are unique in that there are two distinct types of texts: Queries and documents (“asymmetric”), while other tasks only have a single type of text (“symmetric”).</li>
<li>On the QuoraRetrieval dataset, which has been shown to be largely symmetric (Muennighoff, 2022), the playing field is more even with SGPT-5.8B-nli outperforming SGPT- 5.8B-msmarco,</li>
</ul></li>
<li><strong>STS &amp; Summarization</strong>
<ul>
<li>Retrieval models (GTR, SGPT-msmarco) perform badly on STS, while ST5-XXL has the highest performance.</li>
<li>This highlights the bifurcation of the field into separate embedding models for retrieval (asymmetric) and similarity (symmetric) use cases (Muennighoff, 2022).</li>
</ul></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="efficiency" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="efficiency">Efficiency</h2>
<p><strong>Maximum speed</strong> -&gt; Word Embedding models offer maximum speed with Glove taking the lead on both performance and speed, thus making the choice simple in this case</p>
<p><strong>Maximum performance</strong> -&gt; If latency is less important than performance Depending on the task at hand, GTR-XXL, ST5-XXL or SGPT-5.8B may be the right choice,</p>
<p><strong>Speed and Peformance</strong> -&gt; The fine-tuned MPNet and MiniLM models lead the middle cluster making the choice easy.</p>
<hr>
<p>#todo you can check the gte architecture here it’s highly related to the MTEP [[tiny-gte_transformer_model]]</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<ul>
<li>We found model performance on different tasks to vary strongly with no model claiming state-of-the-art on all tasks.</li>
<li>Our studies on scaling behavior, model efficiency and multilinguality revealed various intricacies of models that should ease the decision-making process for future research or industry applications of text embeddings.</li>
</ul>
<hr>
<p>Thanks for reading. If you have any questions, feel free to comment down below or reach out to me on twitter <a href="https://twitter.com/AbdelkareemElk1"><span class="citation" data-cites="AbdelkareemElk1">@AbdelkareemElk1</span></a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h2>
<ul>
<li>https://huggingface.co/blog/mteb</li>
<li>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.07316</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/mteb_encoding/MTEB_massive_text_embedding_benchmark.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 27 Oct 2023 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>tiny-gte “Tiny, yet powerful, it is small in size but packs a lot of power.”</title>
  <link>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/mteb_encoding/tiny-gte_transformer_model.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="table-of-contents" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="table-of-contents">Table of contents</h2>
<p>#definition : This is a&nbsp;<a href="https://www.sbert.net/">sentence-transformers</a>&nbsp;model: It maps sentences &amp; paragraphs to a 384 dimensional dense vector space and can be used for tasks like clustering or semantic search. It is distilled from&nbsp;<code>thenlper/gte-small</code>, with comparable (slightly worse) performance at around half the size.</p>
</section>
<section id="details" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="details">Details</h2>
<ul>
<li>It’s around ~45MB very small compared to other models like MiniLM-L6-V2 which is equal to ~80 MB</li>
<li>Embedding vector size 384d</li>
<li>BERT based</li>
<li>Distilied from thenlper/gte-small,</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="notice-about-using-small-size" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="notice-about-using-small-size">Notice about using small size</h2>
</section>
<section id="use-cases" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="use-cases">Use Cases</h2>
</section>
<section id="todo" class="level1">
<h1>Todo</h1>
<ol type="1">
<li><label><input type="checkbox" checked="">Explain the MTEB</label>
<ol type="1">
<li>Add the link of it into the this blog</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Explain fastembed</li>
<li>Make comparison between tiny-gte and small gte</li>
<li>Add the small-gte-4096 comparison</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level1">
<h1>References</h1>
<ul>
<li>https://huggingface.co/TaylorAI/gte-tiny</li>
<li>https://www.linkedin.com/posts/prithivirajdamodaran_%3F%3F%3F%3F-%3F%3F%3F%3F-%3F%3F%3F%3F%3F-%3F%3F%3F%3F-activity-7120279840569597952-iwc-/?utm_source=share&amp;utm_medium=member_desktop</li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/mteb_encoding/tiny-gte_transformer_model.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 20 Oct 2023 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>havrard CS197 AI research experiences</title>
  <dc:creator>kareem </dc:creator>
  <link>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/courses/havrard CS197 AI research experiences.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="table-of-contents" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="table-of-contents">Table of contents</h2>
<ul class="task-list">
<li><label><input type="checkbox">This course consists of 21 quick lectures that include valuable experiences and important tips for anyone interested in the field of scientific research, especially deep learning. The course can be completed in approximately one or two days. The title is not very precise, and the content of the lectures ranges from about 8 to 26 pages each. Some topics may not be directly related to the specifics of scientific research, but they are generally very helpful lectures for beginners in the field.</label></li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="reviews" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="reviews">Reviews</h2>
<p>Lecture 1: Exciting Advances with AI Language Models <strong>Content</strong> : Interact with language models like GPT-3’s text completion and use Codex’s code generation abilities <strong>feedback</strong> : ⭐ (1/5)</p>
<hr>
<p>Lecture 2: The Zen of python <strong>Content</strong> : vscode,git,conad,linting and Debugging. <strong>feedback</strong>: <strong>feedback</strong> : ⭐ (1/5)</p>
<hr>
<p>Lecture 3: Reading AI Research papers <strong>Content</strong> :</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Conduct a literature search to identify papers relevant to a topic of interest</li>
<li>Difference between Reading Wide and Reading deep and how to balance between them</li>
<li>How to use Google Scholar and paper with code <strong>feedback</strong> : ⭐⭐⭐⭐⭐ (5/5)</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<p>Lecture 4: In-Tune with Jazz Hands <strong>Content</strong>:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>quick intro into huggingface</li>
<li>Tokenization</li>
<li>Causal language modeling (CLM) <strong>feedback</strong> : ⭐⭐⭐⭐ (4/5)</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<p>Lecture 5: Lightning McTorch <strong>Content</strong> :</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Fine-tuning A vision Transformer</li>
<li>Intro to pytorch lightning (Lightning)</li>
<li>Data Loading</li>
<li>How to Build a Neural net Module with lightning and how lightning modules work <strong>feedback</strong> : ⭐⭐⭐⭐ (4/5)</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<p>Lecture 6 &amp; 7: Moonwalking with Pytorch <strong>Content</strong> :</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Pytorch Exercises</li>
<li>Tensors</li>
<li>Autograd and neural networks <strong>feedback</strong> : ⭐ (1/5)</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<p>Lecture 8 &amp; 9: Experiment Organization Spakrs Joy <strong>Content</strong> :</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Weight and Biases</li>
<li>Hyperparameter Search</li>
<li>Hydra <strong>feedback</strong> : ⭐⭐⭐⭐ (4/5)</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<p>Lecture 10 &amp; 11 : I Dreamed a Dream <strong>Content</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Identifying Gaps in A Research Paper
<ol type="1">
<li>CLIP and CheXzero</li>
</ol></li>
<li>Generating Ideas for Building a Research Paper</li>
<li>Iterating on your research ideas <strong>feedback</strong> : ⭐⭐⭐⭐⭐ (5/5)</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<p>Lecture 12 &amp; 13 : Today Was a Fairytale</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>how to deconstruct the elements of a research paper and their sequence</li>
<li>Resulting template that you can use as a general example <strong>feedback</strong> : ⭐⭐⭐⭐ (4/5)</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<p>Lecture 14 &amp; 15: Deep Learning on Cloud Nine <em>didn’t complete it</em> 🙃🙃🙃</p>
<hr>
<p>Lecture 16 &amp; 17:Make your dreams come tuned <strong>Content</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>high level use of Stable Diffusion using a Dreambooth template</li>
<li>Use AWS to accelerate the training of Stable Diffusion models with GPUs</li>
<li>HF Accelerator <strong>feedback</strong> : ⭐⭐ (2/5)</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<p>Lecture 18 : Research Productivity Power-Ups <strong>Content</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>How update meetings and working sessions</li>
<li>organizing your efforts on a project</li>
<li>what is technical dept and examples on it <strong>feedback</strong> : ⭐⭐⭐⭐ (4/5)</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<p>Lecture 19 :The AI Ninja <strong>Content</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>How to make Steady Progress</li>
<li>Some Research Skills</li>
<li>Discussion Questions <strong>feedback</strong> : ⭐⭐ (2/5) I found that <a href="https://colah.github.io/notes/taste/">Colah’ blog</a> content about research is better in the context and offers a great details</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<p>Lecture 20: Bejeweled ⭐⭐⭐⭐⭐(5/5)</p>
<ol type="1">
<li>how to make a slides to improve your research talk</li>
<li>Assertion Evidence Approach <strong>feedback</strong> : ⭐⭐ (2/5) This is great related talk from MIT about this topic <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Unzc731iCUY&amp;pp=ygUyaG93IHRvIG1ha2Ugc2xpZGVzaG93IGFuZCBwcmVzZW50YXRpb24gbWl0IGxlY3R1cmU%3D">How to speak</a> ⭐⭐⭐⭐⭐(5/5)</li>
</ol>
<hr>
<p>Lecture 21 : Model Showdown <strong>Content</strong></p>
<ol type="1">
<li>Statistical Testing <strong>feedback</strong> : ⭐⭐ ⭐(3/5)</li>
</ol>
<hr>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/courses/havrard CS197 AI research experiences.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2023 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>why i am blogging</title>
  <dc:creator>Kareem Elkhateb</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/why_I_am_blogging.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="table-of-contents" class="level2">

</section>
<section id="why-i-am-blogging" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="why-i-am-blogging">Why I am blogging</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>I am blogging to establish a presence on the internet and hope to collaborate with people who are interested in what I write or think about (reducing the search space by reversing the process).</li>
<li>It serves as a resume and blueprint for my existence in this world.</li>
<li>My goal is to help others by providing valuable content that makes their lives easier and better.</li>
<li>Organizing my knowledge and recapping topics I’ve forgotten helps me experience “aha” moments! 💡
<ol type="1">
<li>It’s a test of whether I truly understand something or not.</li>
</ol></li>
<li>I don’t like social media posts, Facebook, Twitter, or LinkedIn articles. I believe these platforms are not the best places for technical blogs, and their disadvantages outweigh the advantages.</li>
<li>I value the freedom of speech. Some topics or thoughts may be censored on social media, but I want to express my opinions without restrictions from others whose opinions I may not respect.</li>
<li>I want to discuss topics while I’m learning them because they’re still fresh in my mind. This will help anyone in a similar position as me in the future.</li>
<li>When studying a topic and knowing that I can write about it on my blog, I find my mind more focused on details that would fit well in the blog. This makes the learning process more enjoyable, focused, and valuable.</li>
<li>I want my posts and knowledge to be more organized!
<ol type="1">
<li>Who will search for a post written six years ago on Facebook or see your first tweet?</li>
<li>This problem is related to the feed of these social platforms.</li>
</ol></li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h2>
<ul>
<li>https://medium.com/<span class="citation" data-cites="racheltho/why-you-yes-you-should-blog-7d2544ac1045">@racheltho/why-you-yes-you-should-blog-7d2544ac1045</span></li>
</ul>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>blogging</category>
  <category>publish</category>
  <guid>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/life_style/why_I_am_blogging.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2023 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How I am using NLP to improve my Websites SEO</title>
  <dc:creator>Kareem Elkhateb</dc:creator>
  <link>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/seo/how_i_use_nlp_for_seo.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p><strong>Unlocking SEO Potential with NLP: A Journey of Website Optimization</strong></p>
<p>In the vast digital landscape, the visibility of a website amidst the sea of search results can make or break its success. Search Engine Optimization (SEO) stands as the beacon guiding businesses towards the shores of higher visibility and traffic. As the digital realm evolves, so do the strategies employed to enhance SEO. One such frontier that holds immense promise is the integration of Natural Language Processing (NLP) into SEO practices.</p>
<section id="understanding-the-landscape" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="understanding-the-landscape">Understanding the Landscape</h3>
<p>SEO isn’t just about optimizing keywords anymore; it’s about understanding user intent, predicting trends, and delivering value-rich content. Harnessing the power of NLP, we embark on a journey to revolutionize SEO practices for our websites. Here’s how we’re leveraging NLP to bolster our SEO efforts:</p>
</section>
<section id="daily-downloads-and-keyword-integration" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="daily-downloads-and-keyword-integration">1. Daily Downloads and Keyword Integration</h3>
<p>We kickstart our journey by integrating Google Search Console into our workflow. By fetching daily downloads of our top queries, we gain invaluable insights into user behavior and preferences. These queries are seamlessly integrated into a specific folder, forming the backbone of our content optimization strategy.</p>
</section>
<section id="content-analysis-and-optimization" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="content-analysis-and-optimization">2. Content Analysis and Optimization</h3>
<p>NLP comes into play as we meticulously analyze our content to ensure alignment with the top queries identified. By leveraging NLP techniques, we ascertain the presence of these keywords within our content, ensuring relevance and resonance with our audience’s search intent.</p>
</section>
<section id="predictive-analytics-and-trend-spotting" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="predictive-analytics-and-trend-spotting">3. Predictive Analytics and Trend Spotting</h3>
<p>Powered by NLP, we delve into the realm of predictive analytics to forecast future trends. By analyzing historical data and current patterns, we identify emerging trends and capitalize on them proactively. This enables us to stay ahead of the curve and position our content strategically to meet evolving user demands.</p>
</section>
<section id="semantic-and-exact-match-integration" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="semantic-and-exact-match-integration">4. Semantic and Exact Match Integration</h3>
<p>NLP empowers us to delve deeper into the semantics of language, enabling us to differentiate between exact matches and similar meanings. Through advanced NLP algorithms, we ensure that our content not only features exact keyword matches but also resonates with synonymous terms, enhancing its visibility across diverse search queries.</p>
</section>
<section id="leveling-up-the-game" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="leveling-up-the-game">Leveling Up the Game</h3>
<p>As we progress on our journey of NLP-driven SEO optimization, we outline a roadmap for leveling up our capabilities:</p>
<section id="level-1" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="level-1">Level 1:</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Data Management</strong>: Implementing robust data storage solutions tailored to multiple websites.</li>
<li><strong>Visualization</strong>: Crafting compelling visualizations using tools like Bokeh and Plotly.</li>
<li><strong>Machine Learning Models</strong>: Developing forecasting models to predict future trends.</li>
<li><strong>Semantic Search</strong>: Leveraging vector databases for semantic and exact search capabilities.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="level-2" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="level-2">Level 2:</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Optimization</strong>: Streamlining our codebase through asynchronous processing and caching mechanisms.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="level-3" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="level-3">Level 3:</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Product Development</strong>: Exploring avenues to transform our NLP-driven SEO framework into software products like WordPress plugins or desktop applications.</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="level-4" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="level-4">Level 4:</h4>
<ul>
<li><strong>Innovation</strong>: Drawing inspiration from industry leaders to create bespoke solutions, such as an Arabic version of our SEO platform akin to UberSuggest and Guni Rank.</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>I mainly using NLP with python to improve my landing pages for home services like the following services: Here are the markdown links with target titles for the provided text:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="https://manaraazel.sa/services/foam-insulation-company-in-medina/">شركة عزل فوم بالمدينة المنورة</a></li>
<li><a href="https://manaraazel.sa/%d8%b4%d8%b1%d9%83%d8%a9-%d8%b9%d8%b2%d9%84-%d9%81%d9%88%d9%85-%d8%a8%d9%85%d9%83%d8%a9/">شركة عزل فوم بمكة</a></li>
<li><a href="https://manaraazel.sa/%d8%b4%d8%b1%d9%83%d8%a9-%d8%b9%d8%b2%d9%84-%d9%81%d9%88%d9%85-%d8%a8%d8%a7%d9%84%d8%b7%d8%a7%d8%a6%d9%81/">شركة عزل فوم بالطائف</a></li>
<li><a href="https://el-harmeen.com/">شركة عزل اسطح بالاحساء</a></li>
<li><a href="https://elharameen.com">شركة عزل اسطح بالدمام</a></li>
<li><a href="https://anwan.me/">منصة صناعة المحتوي العربي</a></li>
<li><a href="https://oudhmotors.com/">حجز موعد فحص المركبات بالدمام</a></li>
<li><a href="https://kamcalorie.com">كم كالوري في الموز</a></li>
</ol>
<p>In the ever-evolving landscape of SEO, the integration of NLP marks a paradigm shift towards more sophisticated and nuanced optimization strategies. By harnessing the power of NLP, we not only decipher the language of search but also anticipate and cater to the evolving needs of our audience. As we continue to refine our approach and explore new frontiers, the synergy between NLP and SEO promises to redefine the digital landscape, empowering businesses to thrive in an era of unparalleled connectivity and discovery. you can read more articles <a href="https://kareemai.com/blog/feed.html">here</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>life</category>
  <category>blogging</category>
  <category>publish</category>
  <category>seo</category>
  <guid>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/seo/how_i_use_nlp_for_seo.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jul 2023 21:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>What is an Array ?</title>
  <link>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/ds_and_algo/Static_array.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<ul>
<li>Static array organize data by holding a collection of elements and making them accessible through an index</li>
<li>We use them to store and iterate over, or manipulate a collection of values of the same type without knowing much about how the individual values are correlated.</li>
<li>you can store integers, fractions, strings and other types of objects.</li>
</ul>
<section id="what-is-adt" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-is-adt">What is ADT ?</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>ADTs are a theoretical concept. more like logical/mathematical view
<ol type="1">
<li>we specify the what part and also potentially the expected performance</li>
<li>It’s independent of a programming language and how it wil be implemented</li>
</ol></li>
<li>E.g Providing a append functionality with capacity enchancement</li>
<li>ADT are acting like an interface</li>
</ol>
<section id="adt-of-array" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="adt-of-array">ADT of Array</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>Stores a collection of data</li>
<li>its elements can be accessed by index</li>
<li>Elements don’t have to be accessed sequentailly; you can get the 10th element wihtout having to read all previous elements before it</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="core-features-of-array" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="core-features-of-array">Core features of Array</h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>Arrays are allocated in memoery as a single, uninterrupted block of memory with sequential locations, which is both memory and time efficient</li>
<li>Arrays are restricted to storing data of the same type. This restrication also stems from the need for optimization because it allows the same memory to be allocated for each element in the array and the compiler/interpreter to quickly know the memory address of each element.</li>
<li>The size of arrays, that is the number of elements contained in an array, must be decided when the array is created, and that size can’t be changed.</li>
</ol>
</section>
</section>
<section id="initialization-for-arrays-in-python" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="initialization-for-arrays-in-python">Initialization for Arrays in Python</h2>
<p>…</p>
</section>
<section id="arrays-in-python" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="arrays-in-python">Arrays in python</h2>
<ul>
<li>python offers the <code>list</code> class as its native array-like solution but it’s a dynamic not static</li>
<li>The closest to array in python is the Python’s array module, which enforces type consistency but is still a dynamic array.</li>
<li>Numpy library is the most similar to static arrays and it’s efficient</li>
</ul>
</section>
<section id="core-array-grokking-code" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="core-array-grokking-code">Core Array grokking code</h2>
<div id="cell-5" class="cell" data-execution_count="1">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode python code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode python"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">import</span> array</span>
<span id="cb1-2"><span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">from</span> typing <span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">import</span> Union</span>
<span id="cb1-3"></span>
<span id="cb1-4"></span>
<span id="cb1-5"><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">class</span> Array:</span>
<span id="cb1-6">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__init__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, size: <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>, typecode: <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">str</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"l"</span>):</span>
<span id="cb1-7">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;=</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span>:</span>
<span id="cb1-8">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">raise</span> <span class="pp" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ValueError</span>(<span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">f"Invalid array size (must be positive): </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">{</span>size<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-9">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> size</span>
<span id="cb1-10">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> array.array(typecode, [<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span>] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span> size)</span>
<span id="cb1-11"></span>
<span id="cb1-12">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__len__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>):</span>
<span id="cb1-13">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size</span>
<span id="cb1-14"></span>
<span id="cb1-15">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__getitem__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, index: <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span> Union[<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>, <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">float</span>]:</span>
<span id="cb1-16">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> index <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span> <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">or</span> index <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&gt;</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size:</span>
<span id="cb1-17">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">raise</span> <span class="pp" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">IndexError</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"array index out of range"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-18">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">raise</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[index]</span>
<span id="cb1-19"></span>
<span id="cb1-20">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__setitem__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, index: <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>, val: Union[<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>, <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">float</span>]) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">None</span>:</span>
<span id="cb1-21">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> index <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span> <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">or</span> index <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&gt;=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size:</span>
<span id="cb1-22">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">raise</span> <span class="pp" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">IndexError</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"array assignment index out of range"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-23">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[index] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> val</span>
<span id="cb1-24"></span>
<span id="cb1-25">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__repr__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>):</span>
<span id="cb1-26">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">repr</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array)</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="unsorted-array" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="unsorted-array">Unsorted Array</h2>
<div id="cell-7" class="cell" data-execution_count="2">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb2" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode python code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode python"><span id="cb2-1"><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">class</span> UnsortedArray:</span>
<span id="cb2-2">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__init__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, max_size: <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>, typecode: <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">str</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"l"</span>):</span>
<span id="cb2-3">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> Array(max_size, typecode)</span>
<span id="cb2-4">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._max_size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> max_size</span>
<span id="cb2-5">        <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># the actual number of elements stored in the array</span></span>
<span id="cb2-6">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span></span>
<span id="cb2-7"></span>
<span id="cb2-8">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__len__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>:</span>
<span id="cb2-9">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size</span>
<span id="cb2-10"></span>
<span id="cb2-11">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__getitem__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, index) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span> Union[<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>, <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">float</span>]:</span>
<span id="cb2-12">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> index <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span> <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">or</span> index <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&gt;=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size:</span>
<span id="cb2-13">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">raise</span> <span class="pp" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">IndexError</span>(<span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">f"Index out of bound : </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">{</span>index<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb2-14">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[index]</span>
<span id="cb2-15"></span>
<span id="cb2-16">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__repr__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">str</span>:</span>
<span id="cb2-17">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">f"UnsortedArray </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">{</span><span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">repr</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array._array[:<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size])<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"</span></span>
<span id="cb2-18"></span>
<span id="cb2-19">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> max_size(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>:</span>
<span id="cb2-20">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._max_size</span>
<span id="cb2-21"></span>
<span id="cb2-22">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> insert(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, new_entry) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">None</span>:</span>
<span id="cb2-23">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&gt;=</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">len</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array):</span>
<span id="cb2-24">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">raise</span> <span class="pp" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ValueError</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"The array is alread fu"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb2-25">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">else</span>:</span>
<span id="cb2-26">            <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> new_entry</span>
<span id="cb2-27">            <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+=</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span></span>
<span id="cb2-28"></span>
<span id="cb2-29">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> delete(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, index) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">None</span>:</span>
<span id="cb2-30">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">==</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span>:</span>
<span id="cb2-31">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">raise</span> <span class="pp" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ValueError</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Delete from an empty array"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb2-32">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">elif</span> index <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span> <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">or</span> index <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&gt;=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size:</span>
<span id="cb2-33">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">raise</span> <span class="pp" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ValueError</span>(<span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">f"Index </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">{</span>index<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> out of range"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb2-34">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">else</span>:</span>
<span id="cb2-35">            <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[index] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>]</span>
<span id="cb2-36">            <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-=</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span></span>
<span id="cb2-37"></span>
<span id="cb2-38">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> find(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, target) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>:</span>
<span id="cb2-39">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> index <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span>, <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size):</span>
<span id="cb2-40">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[index] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">==</span> target:</span>
<span id="cb2-41">                <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> index</span>
<span id="cb2-42">        <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># couldn't find the target</span></span>
<span id="cb2-43">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">None</span></span>
<span id="cb2-44"></span>
<span id="cb2-45">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> traverse(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, callback):</span>
<span id="cb2-46">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> index <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size):</span>
<span id="cb2-47">            callback(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[index])</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="sorted-arrays" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sorted-arrays">Sorted Arrays</h2>
<p>for sorted arrays, encapsulation becomes even more important because we need to guarantee another invariant : that the elements in the array are always sorted.</p>
<div id="cell-9" class="cell" data-execution_count="3">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb3" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode python code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode python"><span id="cb3-1"><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">class</span> sortedArray:</span>
<span id="cb3-2">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__init__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, max_size: <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>, typecode: <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">str</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"l"</span>):</span>
<span id="cb3-3">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> Array(max_size, typecode)</span>
<span id="cb3-4">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._max_size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> max_size</span>
<span id="cb3-5"></span>
<span id="cb3-6">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span></span>
<span id="cb3-7"></span>
<span id="cb3-8">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__len__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>:</span>
<span id="cb3-9">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size</span>
<span id="cb3-10"></span>
<span id="cb3-11">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__getitem__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, index) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span> Union[<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>, <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">float</span>]:</span>
<span id="cb3-12">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> index <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span> <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">or</span> index <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&gt;=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size:</span>
<span id="cb3-13">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">raise</span> <span class="pp" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ValueError</span>(<span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">f"Index out of bound: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">{</span>index<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb3-14">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[index]</span>
<span id="cb3-15">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__repr__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span><span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">str</span>:</span>
<span id="cb3-16">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">f"Sorted Array (</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">{</span><span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">repr</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array._array[:<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size])<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">)"</span></span>
<span id="cb3-17">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__iter__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>):</span>
<span id="cb3-18">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> i <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size):</span>
<span id="cb3-19">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">yield</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[i]</span>
<span id="cb3-20">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> max_size(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span><span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>:</span>
<span id="cb3-21">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._max_size</span>
<span id="cb3-22">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> insert(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>,value:Union[<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>,<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">float</span>])<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span><span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">None</span>:</span>
<span id="cb3-23">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&gt;=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._max_size:</span>
<span id="cb3-24">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">raise</span> <span class="pp" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ValueError</span>(<span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">f"The array is already full, maximum size:</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">{</span><span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span>_max_size<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb3-25">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> i <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size,<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span>,<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>):</span>
<span id="cb3-26">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[i<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;=</span>value:</span>
<span id="cb3-27">                <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[i] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> value</span>
<span id="cb3-28">                <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span> </span>
<span id="cb3-29">                <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> </span>
<span id="cb3-30">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">else</span>:</span>
<span id="cb3-31">                <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[i] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[i<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>]</span>
<span id="cb3-32">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span>] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> value</span>
<span id="cb3-33">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span></span>
<span id="cb3-34">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> linear_search(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>,target:Union[<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>,<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">float</span>])<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span>Union[<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>,<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">None</span>]:</span>
<span id="cb3-35">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> i <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size):</span>
<span id="cb3-36">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[i]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">==</span>target:</span>
<span id="cb3-37">                <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> i</span>
<span id="cb3-38">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">elif</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[i]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&gt;</span>target:</span>
<span id="cb3-39">                <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">None</span></span>
<span id="cb3-40">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">None</span></span>
<span id="cb3-41">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> binary_search(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>,target:Union[<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>,<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">float</span>])<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span>Union[<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>,<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">None</span>]:</span>
<span id="cb3-42">        left <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span></span>
<span id="cb3-43">        right <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span></span>
<span id="cb3-44">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">while</span> left <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;=</span>right:</span>
<span id="cb3-45">            mid_index <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> (left<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span>right) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">//</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">2</span></span>
<span id="cb3-46">            mid_val <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[mid_index]</span>
<span id="cb3-47">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> mid_val<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">==</span> target:</span>
<span id="cb3-48">                <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> mid_index</span>
<span id="cb3-49">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">elif</span> mid_val <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&gt;</span> target:</span>
<span id="cb3-50">                right <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> mid_index <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span></span>
<span id="cb3-51">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">else</span>:</span>
<span id="cb3-52">                left <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> mid_index  <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span></span>
<span id="cb3-53">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">None</span></span>
<span id="cb3-54">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> delete(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>,target:Union[<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>,<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">float</span>])<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span><span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">None</span>:</span>
<span id="cb3-55">        index <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.binary_search(target)</span>
<span id="cb3-56">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> index <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">is</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">None</span>:</span>
<span id="cb3-57">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">raise</span> <span class="pp" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ValueError</span>(<span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">f"Unable to delete element</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">{</span>target<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">: the entry is not in the array"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb3-58">        </span>
<span id="cb3-59">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> i <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(index,<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>):</span>
<span id="cb3-60">            <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[i] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[i<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>]</span>
<span id="cb3-61">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span></span></code></pre></div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="profiling" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="profiling">Profiling</h2>
<p>…</p>
</section>
<section id="asymptotic-analysis" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="asymptotic-analysis">Asymptotic analysis</h2>
<p>…</p>
</section>
<section id="big-o-notation" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="big-o-notation">Big-O notation</h2>
<p>…</p>
<p>• To evaluate the performance of an algorithm, we can use asymptotic analysis, which means finding out a formula, expressed in big-O notation, that describes the behavior of the algorithm on the RAM model.</p>
<p>• The RAM model is a simplified computational model of a generic computer that provides only a limited set of basic instructions, all of which take constant time.</p>
<p>• Big-O notation is used to classify functions based on their asymptotic growth. We use these classes of functions to express how fast the running time or memory used by an algorithm grows as the input becomes larger.</p>
<p>• Some of the most common classes of functions, the ones you will see more often are</p>
<pre><code>– O(1)–constant—Whenever a resource grows independently of n (for example, a basic instruction).

– O(log(n))–logarithmic—Slow growth, like binary search.

– O(n)–linear—A function that grows at the same rate as the input, like the number of comparisons you need in a linear search.

– O(n*log(n))–linearithmic—We’ll see this order of growth for priority queues.

– O(n2)–quadratic—Functions in this class grow too fast for resources to be manageable beyond about a million elements. An example is the number of pairs in an array.

– O(2n)–exponential—Functions with exponential growth have huge values for n &gt; 30 already. So if you want to compute all the subsets of an array, you should know that you can only do this on small arrays</code></pre>
</section>
<section id="dyanmic-arrays" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dyanmic-arrays">Dyanmic Arrays</h2>
<p>• Arrays are great containers when we need to access elements based on their position. They provide constant-time access to any element, and we can read or write any element without sequentially accessing the elements before it.</p>
<p>• However, arrays are inherently static. That is, because of the way they are implemented in memory, their size cannot be changed once they are created.</p>
<p>• Having a fixed-size container means that we can’t be flexible if we find that we need to store more elements. Furthermore, allocating a large array from the start to support the largest possible number of elements is often a waste of memory.</p>
<p>• Dynamic arrays are a way to get the best of arrays and add some flexibility. They are not a different type of data structure. They use fixed-size arrays but add a strategy to grow and shrink them as needed, reallocating the underlying static array each time it needs to be resized.</p>
<p>• The best strategy for dynamic arrays is to double the size of the underlying static array when we try to insert a new element into a full array and halve the size of the array when, after removing an element, three-quarters of the elements are empty</p>
<p>• This flexibility comes at a cost: insert and delete can’t be constant time as they are for static unsorted arrays. But for the insert method (and, under some assumptions, for the delete method as well), we can guarantee that n operations take an O(n) amortized running time and additional memor</p>
<div id="cell-12" class="cell" data-execution_count="5">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb5" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode python code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode python"><span id="cb5-1"><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">class</span> DyanmicArray:</span>
<span id="cb5-2">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__init__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, initial_capacity: <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>, typecode: <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">str</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"l"</span>) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">None</span>:</span>
<span id="cb5-3">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> Array(initial_capacity, typecode)</span>
<span id="cb5-4">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._capacity <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> initial_capacity</span>
<span id="cb5-5">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span></span>
<span id="cb5-6">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._typecode <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> typecode</span>
<span id="cb5-7"></span>
<span id="cb5-8">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__len__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>:</span>
<span id="cb5-9">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size</span>
<span id="cb5-10"></span>
<span id="cb5-11">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__getitem__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, index) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span> Union[<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>, <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">float</span>]:</span>
<span id="cb5-12">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> index <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&gt;=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.size:</span>
<span id="cb5-13">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">raise</span> <span class="pp" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">IndexError</span>(<span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">f"Index out of bound: </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">{</span>index<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb5-14">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[index]</span>
<span id="cb5-15"></span>
<span id="cb5-16">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__repr__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">str</span>:</span>
<span id="cb5-17">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">repr</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array._array[: <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size])</span>
<span id="cb5-18"></span>
<span id="cb5-19">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__iter__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>):</span>
<span id="cb5-20">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> i <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size):</span>
<span id="cb5-21">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">yield</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[i]</span>
<span id="cb5-22"></span>
<span id="cb5-23">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> _is_full(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>):</span>
<span id="cb5-24">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&gt;=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._capacity</span>
<span id="cb5-25"></span>
<span id="cb5-26">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> _double_size(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>):</span>
<span id="cb5-27">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">assert</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._capacity <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">==</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size</span>
<span id="cb5-28">        old_array <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array</span>
<span id="cb5-29">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> Array(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._capacity <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">2</span>, <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._typecode)</span>
<span id="cb5-30">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._capacity <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*=</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">2</span></span>
<span id="cb5-31">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> i <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size):</span>
<span id="cb5-32">            <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[i] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> old_array[i]</span>
<span id="cb5-33">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">assert</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array._size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">==</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._capacity</span>
<span id="cb5-34"></span>
<span id="cb5-35">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> _halve_size(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>):</span>
<span id="cb5-36">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">assert</span> (</span>
<span id="cb5-37">            <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._capacity <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&gt;</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span> <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">and</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._capacity <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">/</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">4</span></span>
<span id="cb5-38">        )  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Invariant: this is called only when capacity &gt; 1 and size &lt;= capacity/4</span></span>
<span id="cb5-39">        old_array <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array</span>
<span id="cb5-40">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">==</span> Array(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._capacity <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">//</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">2</span>, <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._typecode)</span>
<span id="cb5-41">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._capacity <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">//=</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">2</span></span>
<span id="cb5-42">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> i <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size):</span>
<span id="cb5-43">            <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[i] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> old_array[i]</span>
<span id="cb5-44">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">assert</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array._size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">==</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._capacity</span>
<span id="cb5-45"></span>
<span id="cb5-46">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> is_empty(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>):</span>
<span id="cb5-47">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">len</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">==</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span></span>
<span id="cb5-48"></span>
<span id="cb5-49">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> insert(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, value: Union[<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>, <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">float</span>]) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">None</span>:</span>
<span id="cb5-50">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._is_full():</span>
<span id="cb5-51">            <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._double_size()</span>
<span id="cb5-52">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> value</span>
<span id="cb5-53"></span>
<span id="cb5-54">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> find(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, target: Union[<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>, <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">float</span>]) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span> Union[<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>, <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">None</span>]:</span>
<span id="cb5-55">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> i <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size):</span>
<span id="cb5-56">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[i] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">==</span> target:</span>
<span id="cb5-57">                <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> i</span>
<span id="cb5-58">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">None</span></span>
<span id="cb5-59"></span>
<span id="cb5-60">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> delete(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, target: Union[<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">int</span>, <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">float</span>]) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-&gt;</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">None</span>:</span>
<span id="cb5-61">        index <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.find(target)</span>
<span id="cb5-62">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> index <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">is</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">None</span>:</span>
<span id="cb5-63">            <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">raise</span> <span class="pp" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">ValueError</span>(</span>
<span id="cb5-64">                <span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">f"Unable to delete element </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">{</span>target<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"> the entry is not in the array"</span></span>
<span id="cb5-65">            )</span>
<span id="cb5-66">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> i <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(index, <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>):</span>
<span id="cb5-67">            <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[i] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._array[i <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>]</span>
<span id="cb5-68">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-=</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span></span>
<span id="cb5-69">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._capacity <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&gt;</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span> <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">and</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._capacity <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">/</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">4</span>:</span>
<span id="cb5-70">            <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._halve_size()</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="creating-actual-c-array-in-python" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="creating-actual-c-array-in-python">Creating actual C array in python</h2>
<ul>
<li>The ctype module allows us to create a C array of FIXED size</li>
</ul>
<div id="cell-14" class="cell" data-execution_count="11">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb6" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode python code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode python"><span id="cb6-1"><span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">import</span> ctypes</span>
<span id="cb6-2"></span>
<span id="cb6-3"></span>
<span id="cb6-4"><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">class</span> Array:</span>
<span id="cb6-5">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__init__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, size):</span>
<span id="cb6-6">        array_data_type <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> ctypes.py_object <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span> size</span>
<span id="cb6-7">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> size</span>
<span id="cb6-8">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.memory <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> array_data_type()</span>
<span id="cb6-9"></span>
<span id="cb6-10">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> i <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(size):</span>
<span id="cb6-11">            <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.memory[i] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">None</span></span>
<span id="cb6-12"></span>
<span id="cb6-13">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__len__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>):</span>
<span id="cb6-14">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.size</span>
<span id="cb6-15"></span>
<span id="cb6-16">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__getitem__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, idx):</span>
<span id="cb6-17">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.memory[idx]  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># Is valid idx?</span></span>
<span id="cb6-18"></span>
<span id="cb6-19">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__setitem__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, idx, value):</span>
<span id="cb6-20">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.memory[idx] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> value</span>
<span id="cb6-21"></span>
<span id="cb6-22">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__repr__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>):</span>
<span id="cb6-23">        result <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">""</span></span>
<span id="cb6-24">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> i <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.size):</span>
<span id="cb6-25">            result <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+=</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">str</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.memory[i]) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">", "</span></span>
<span id="cb6-26">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> result</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
<div id="cell-15" class="cell" data-execution_count="12">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb7" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode python code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode python"><span id="cb7-1">array <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> Array(<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">6</span>) <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">#fixed array </span></span>
<span id="cb7-2"><span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> i <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(array.size):</span>
<span id="cb7-3">    array.memory[i]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> i<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span></span>
<span id="cb7-4"><span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> i <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(array.size):</span>
<span id="cb7-5">    <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">print</span>(array.memory[i])</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>1
2
3
4
5
6</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
<div id="cell-16" class="cell" data-execution_count="14">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb9" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode python code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode python"><span id="cb9-1">array <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> Array(<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">6</span>)</span>
<span id="cb9-2"><span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> i <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">len</span>(array)):</span>
<span id="cb9-3">    array[i] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> i <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span></span>
<span id="cb9-4"></span>
<span id="cb9-5"><span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> i <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(<span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">len</span>(array)):</span>
<span id="cb9-6">    <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">print</span>(array[i],end<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">","</span>)</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-stdout">
<pre><code>1,2,3,4,5,6,</code></pre>
</div>
</div>
<div id="cell-17" class="cell" data-execution_count="13">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb11" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode python code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode python"><span id="cb11-1"><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">del</span> array.memory[<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span>]</span></code></pre></div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-error">
<div class="ansi-escaped-output">
<pre><span class="ansi-red-fg">---------------------------------------------------------------------------</span>
<span class="ansi-red-fg">TypeError</span>                                 Traceback (most recent call last)
Cell <span class="ansi-green-fg">In[13], line 1</span>
<span class="ansi-green-fg">----&gt; 1</span> <span style="font-weight:bold;color:rgb(0,135,0)">del</span> array<span style="color:rgb(98,98,98)">.</span>memory[<span style="color:rgb(98,98,98)">0</span>]

<span class="ansi-red-fg">TypeError</span>: Array does not support item deletion</pre>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div id="cell-18" class="cell" data-execution_count="10">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb12" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode python code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode python"><span id="cb12-1"><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">del</span> array.memory</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="full-array-code" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="full-array-code">Full Array code</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li>append</li>
<li>expand</li>
<li>insert ..etc</li>
</ol>
<div id="cell-20" class="cell">
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb13" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode python code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode python"><span id="cb13-1"><span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">import</span> ctypes</span>
<span id="cb13-2"></span>
<span id="cb13-3"></span>
<span id="cb13-4"><span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">class</span> Array:</span>
<span id="cb13-5">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__init__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, size):</span>
<span id="cb13-6">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> size</span>
<span id="cb13-7">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._capacity <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">max</span>(<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">16</span>, <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">2</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span> size)  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># actual memory size</span></span>
<span id="cb13-8">        array_data_type <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> ctypes.py_object <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._capacity</span>
<span id="cb13-9">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.memory <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> array_data_type()</span>
<span id="cb13-10"></span>
<span id="cb13-11">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> i <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._capacity):</span>
<span id="cb13-12">            <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.memory[i] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">None</span></span>
<span id="cb13-13"></span>
<span id="cb13-14">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> expand_capacity(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>):</span>
<span id="cb13-15">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._capacity <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*=</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">2</span></span>
<span id="cb13-16">        <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">print</span>(<span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">f"Expand capacity to </span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">{</span><span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span><span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">.</span>_capacity<span class="sc" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">}</span><span class="ss" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"</span>)</span>
<span id="cb13-17"></span>
<span id="cb13-18">        array_data_type <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> ctypes.py_object <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">*</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._capacity</span>
<span id="cb13-19">        new_memory <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> array_data_type()</span>
<span id="cb13-20">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> i <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.size):</span>
<span id="cb13-21">            new_memory[i] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.memory[i]</span>
<span id="cb13-22"></span>
<span id="cb13-23">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> append(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, item):</span>
<span id="cb13-24">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">==</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._capacity:</span>
<span id="cb13-25">            <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.expand_capacity()</span>
<span id="cb13-26">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.memory[<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.size] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> item</span>
<span id="cb13-27">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+=</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span></span>
<span id="cb13-28"></span>
<span id="cb13-29">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> insert(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>, idx, item):</span>
<span id="cb13-30">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">assert</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span> <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;=</span> idx <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">&lt;</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.size</span>
<span id="cb13-31">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">if</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">==</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>._capacity:</span>
<span id="cb13-32">            <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.expand_capacity()</span>
<span id="cb13-33"></span>
<span id="cb13-34">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> p <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>, idx <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>, <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">-</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>):</span>
<span id="cb13-35">            <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.memory[p <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.memory[p]</span>
<span id="cb13-36">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.memory[idx] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> item</span>
<span id="cb13-37">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.size <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+=</span> <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span></span>
<span id="cb13-38">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__len__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>):</span>
<span id="cb13-39">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.size</span>
<span id="cb13-40">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__getitem__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>,idx):</span>
<span id="cb13-41">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.memory[idx]</span>
<span id="cb13-42">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__setitem__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>,idx,value):</span>
<span id="cb13-43">        <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.memory[idx]<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> value</span>
<span id="cb13-44">    <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">def</span> <span class="fu" style="color: #4758AB;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">__repr__</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>):</span>
<span id="cb13-45">        result <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">''</span></span>
<span id="cb13-46">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">for</span> i <span class="kw" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">in</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">range</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.size):</span>
<span id="cb13-47">            result <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+=</span> <span class="bu" style="color: null;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">str</span>(<span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">self</span>.memory[i]) <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">+</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">', '</span></span>
<span id="cb13-48">        <span class="cf" style="color: #003B4F;
background-color: null;
font-weight: bold;
font-style: inherit;">return</span> result</span></code></pre></div>
</div>
</section>
<section id="array-problems" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="array-problems">Array Problems</h2>
<section id="ms-course-problems" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="ms-course-problems"><a href="https://www.udemy.com/course/python-ds-skills/">MS course problems</a></h3>
<ol type="1">
<li>Negative indexing : allow negative indexing</li>
<li>Right rotation: function that shifts every element 1 step toward the right and the rightmost element goes to the first index</li>
<li>Left rotation : that same as right rotation but to the left</li>
<li>right rotation with steps: how to implement big numbers like 1e5 right rotation in efficient way</li>
<li>pop a position: take the idx of element and return the index of it and delete it from the array no new memory creation and code is very efficient if the removed element is the last one</li>
<li>Improved search : each time you find the value in an array shift it one step to the left</li>
<li>2D Array : creat a fixed grid of requested rows and columns</li>
</ol>
</section>
<section id="neetcode-array-problems" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="neetcode-array-problems"><a href="https://neetcode.io/roadmap">Neetcode Array problems</a></h3>
<ul>
<li>Contains Duplicate</li>
<li>Valid Anagram</li>
<li>Two Sum</li>
<li>Group Anagrams</li>
<li>Top K Frequent Elements</li>
<li>Product of Array Except Self</li>
<li>Valid Sudoku</li>
<li>Longest Consecutive Sequence</li>
</ul>
</section>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="references">References</h2>
<ol type="1">
<li><a href="https://www.manning.com/books/grokking-data-structures">Grokking Data Structures</a></li>
</ol>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <guid>https://kareemai.com/blog/posts/ds_and_algo/Static_array.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 05:26:11 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
